<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dos pou sto, or, An answer to Sure footing, so far as Mr. Whitby is concerned in it wherein the rule and guide of faith, the interest of reason, and the authority of the church in matters of faith, are fully handled and vindicated, from the exceptions of Mr. Serjeant, and petty flirts of Fiat lux : together with An answer to five questions propounded by a Roman Catholick / by Daniel Whitby ...</title>
            <author>Whitby, Daniel, 1638-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38592</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17803154</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17803154</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106628</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65702)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1109:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dos pou sto, or, An answer to Sure footing, so far as Mr. Whitby is concerned in it wherein the rule and guide of faith, the interest of reason, and the authority of the church in matters of faith, are fully handled and vindicated, from the exceptions of Mr. Serjeant, and petty flirts of Fiat lux : together with An answer to five questions propounded by a Roman Catholick / by Daniel Whitby ...</title>
                  <author>Whitby, Daniel, 1638-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 73 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Hall, for R. Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First three words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, Robertus Say, vice-cancellarius Oxon."--Opposite t.p.</note>
                  <note>"An appendix containing an answer to those few passages in Fiat lux which beare some shew of reason, and might possibly deceive the unwary reader": p. 71-73.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: "An answer to five questions propounded by a Roman Catholick" lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sergeant, John, 1622-1707. --  Sure-footing in Christianity.</term>
               <term>J. V. C. --  (John Vincent Canes), d. 1672. --  Fiat lux.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Rule of faith.</term>
               <term>Authority --  Religious aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106628:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106628:1"/>
            <p>ΔΟΣ ΠΟΥ ΣΤΟ OR, AN ANSWER TO Sure Footing, So far as Mr. <hi>Whitby</hi> is concerned in it. Wherein the Rule and Guide of Faith, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Reaſon, and the Authority of the Church in Matters of Faith, are fully handled and vindicated; FROM THE Exceptions of Mr. <hi>SERJEANT,</hi> AND Petty Flirts of <hi>FIAT LUX.</hi> Together with AN ANSWER to <hi>Five Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> propounded by a <hi>ROMAN CATHOLICK.</hi> By <hi>Daniel Whitby,</hi> M. A. Coll. Trin. Oxon. Soc.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD:</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Hall,</hi> for <hi>R. Davis.</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:106628:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>ROBERTUS SAY,</hi> VICE-CANCELLARIUS OXON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106628:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Animadverſions of Mr. <hi>Serjeant</hi> being confuſed and immethodical, would not admit an Anſwer in that Order in which they lie, wherefore I have reduced them to their ſeveral heads, and as I hope, ſufficiently diſcovered the weakneſs of them in the following Chapters, ſtill being careful that I did not <hi>actum agere,</hi> or ſay any thing which might interfer with his two great Antagoniſts; I have ſince been aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a ſecond Sampſon, willing perhaps to ſhew the world what Execution he could do with the Jaw bone of an Aſſe. He hath three paſſages in his Epiſtle which ſeem
<pb facs="tcp:106628:3"/>guilty of a little reaſon, and ſhew he has ſome lucid Intervals which therefore ſhall receive an Anſwer.</p>
            <p>But as for his continual falſifications of my words and arguments, his Wit and Drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, his <hi>Any mad verſions,</hi> and his <hi>white Boys,</hi> (that is, the reſidue of his Epiſtle) I ſhall leave them to be bound up with <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driaſduſt Toſoffacan,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And reſt, <hi>Thy Friend and Servant, DANIEL WHITBY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106628:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the certainty of Faith, and the uſe of Reaſon in matters of Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop:</hi> 1. REaſon is that faculty which God hath given us to diſcern betwixt true and falſe, good or evil, juſt and unjuſt: For that we do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern betwixt theſe things, is every Mans experience, and that we do it by the exerciſe of Reaſon, is moſt evident; for Judgement muſt be either brutiſh, or founded upon Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coroll:</hi> If then my reaſon doth determine what is juſt or unjuſt, good or evil, true or falſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently what is to be done, believed, thought or not, Reaſon muſt be my judge in every caſe. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, To judge, is to determine from ſome ground, and that is to infer or reaſon, and therefore nothing can be judge in any caſe but Reaſon. Thirdly, The Papiſt muſt acknowledge Reaſon for his Judge in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caſe; for either Reaſon muſt aſſure them that the Church in her Traditions is infallible, or elſe they muſt believe it, they know not why, this done, what is unqueſtionably the Tradition of the Church, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be matter of a doubt; and when 'tis doubted or diſputed what is the voice of holy Church, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106628:4"/>muſt ſtill become their Judge, for ſure they muſt have motives to encline them either way? And they are Reaſons, wherefore in all caſes Reaſon is their Judge: and were it not the greateſt folly to offer Reaſons to convince us of the Roman Faith, and at the ſame time tell us its judgement is not to be taken?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object:</hi> But here you preſently throw in, <hi>p.</hi> 187. <hi>The exiſtence of the Trinity,</hi> and then cry out, <hi>To work now with your Reaſon, and ſee how you evince it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Do you believe the aſſertion to be true, or not? if true, Why do you then diſupte againſt it? if not, Why do you not return ſome Anſwer to thoſe Arguments wherewith it was confirmed? nay, why do you acknowledge, That <hi>in great part</hi> of the whole Section, and <hi>eſpecially at the beginning, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is rightly made, p.</hi> 180. ſince that Diſcourſe is viſibly a Complex of Arguments, profeſſedly evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing this concluſion? But Secondly, I conclude the exiſtence of a Trinity by rational Inference from ſuch Scriptures, which affirm, That God is one, and that the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are truly God; and therefore do aſſert it, becauſe my reaſon judgeth theſe Inferences to be valid: and the <hi>Sacinian,</hi> who rejects the Article, doth not reject the Authority of thoſe Scriptures upon which I ground it, but onely endeavors to evade the Inferences of my reaſon from thence: Thus then you ſee, that Reaſon acting on my rule of Faith, produceth this aſſent. And tell me, Are we not enjoyned to give a reaſon of our Faith, and ſo of this as well as other Articles, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to acquaint the Enquirer, why we judge it neceſſary to believe the Exiſtence of a Trinity? You indeed teach me to ſpeak thus, <hi>That I have reaſon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106628:4"/>to believe Authority, and Authority to believe the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Anſw:</hi> True, but I muſt ſtill have reaſon to conclude it from Authority; for it is not formally contain'd in Scripture, but onely thence inferr'd by reaſon, ſo that I have here Divine Authority for my Rule, and Reaſon for my Guide to apply the Rule unto the Article, and infer it thence.</p>
               <p>Object: <hi>Belief is as properly relative to Authority, as Science is to an act of Reaſon; whence 'tis as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous to ſay, I muſt have reaſon to believe ſuch a Point, as to ſay, I know ſuch a Point ſcientifically by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> p. 187.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> As incongruous as it is, I hope you do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the exiſtence of a Diety, the Divine Authority of Scriptures, and the truth of Chriſts Miracles, and that you have reaſon ſo to do; and do you not now ſee the ſtrange and monſtrous incongruity of ſaying, <hi>You have reaſon to believe?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exerc. <hi>3.</hi> Art. <hi>3.</hi> Sect. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> his <hi>hand maid to Divinity</hi> will teach you to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt Faith ſtrictly taken <hi>for an aſſent built upon the Teſtimony of another,</hi> in which ſenſe it is relative to Authority; or more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, and ſo <hi>in Scripture and approved Authors, it denotes any manner of aſſent: thus we are ſaid to believe our eyes,</hi> and Heathens, without a Revelation, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Diety. And laſtly, this or that to be the ſenſe of Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop:</hi> 2. It is confeſs'd on both ſides, and in it ſelf moſt certain, That the foundation of all our Faith depends on Reaſon, and is ultimately reſolved into it, the Proteſtant hath his internal and external Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to induce him to believe the Divine Authority of Scripture; the Papiſt, for his <hi>upſtart Tradition,</hi> pretends no leſs then a <hi>Demonſtration;</hi> and for his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106628:5"/>Churches Authority, he hath his <hi>motives of credibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to produce. And certain it is that, all our Faith and Religion depends upon the Being of a God, and that aſſurance which we have, <hi>That his veracity is ſuch, as will not ſuffer him to deceive us; His goodneſs ſuch, as will not ſuffer us to be invincibly deceived, to our ſouls deſtruction; nor let his providence be wanting in providing for, and preſerving to us that rule of Faith, without which, ſalvation cannot be attained:</hi> unleſs we are aſſured of theſe things, how know we but that God may have deceived the World with falſe Miracles? yea, that he hath not Imprinted in us ſuch diſpoſitions as may continually incline us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Error? That he hath not aſsiſted the Apoſtles, and firſt Promoters of Chriſtianity in delivering to us a falſe Scripture, and falſe Traditions? And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain (Secondly) it is, we have no evidence of theſe things, but that of Reaſon, and conſequently that the whole certainty of Faith depends upon it; and this is freely acknowledged by Mr. <hi>Serjeant,</hi> in his fourth Section, where he tells us, <hi>That our aſſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Authority</hi> is at laſt <hi>reſolved into Reaſon;</hi> and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follows from his grand Aſſertion, <hi>p.</hi> 181. <hi>That no Authority</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> whether of Church, Scripture, or Tradition) <hi>deſerves aſſent farther then true reaſon gives it to deſerve;</hi> and conſequently it muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to true reaſon for the aſſent we yield unto it. And yet I am confidently rebuked for ſaying, That <hi>if</hi> S.C. <hi>believes his church infallible, becauſe his reaſon judgeth it to be ſo, the Church is beholden to the judgement of his private reaſon, for his belief of her infallibility, p.</hi> 96. as if her infallibility could be believ'd <hi>on this very account: deſerve aſſent upon no other,</hi> and the rationalneſs of aſſenting to it could <hi>be reſolved
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106628:5"/>into reaſon,</hi> and ſhe not be beholding to the confeſſed yea the only cauſe of this aſſent for the belief of that infallibility, which is the effect thereof; and all this forſooth, <hi>Becauſe I therefore come to have that Judgment of her infallibility, becauſe ſhe as an object wrought upon my apprehenſion, and imprinted a conceit of her there, as ſhe was in her ſelf, and ſo obliged my Reaſon to conclude, and my judgement to hold her ſuch as ſhe is: pag.</hi> 182. A very deep diſcourſe and able to evince that no man is beholding to his Reaſon for any thing he aſſents unto, but contrarily his Reaſon is beholding to the Object for cauſing that aſſent. <hi>Seing that object works upon his apprehenſion, and imprints a conceit of it ſelf there, as in it ſelf, and ſo obligeth our Reaſon to conclude, and our Judgment to hold it ſuch, as it is,</hi> but Sir, is your aſſent ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or not? If not 'tis Bruitiſh and Abſurd, it may he falſe, nor have you any reaſon to believe it true. If ſo, then muſt you be beholding to your Reaſon for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coroll.</hi> Hence I infer, That Reaſon cannot be rejected, as unſure, and unſufficient to ground an Article of Faith upon; for the certainty of our whole Faith depending upon that of Reaſon, it muſt fall together with it. So that to quarel with the uſe of Reaſon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account, (as Papiſts uſually do) is in effect to quarrel with Religion and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. The certainty of Faith, cannot be greater then that of Science or Mathematical Demonſtration, for that (ſuppoſing only as the fundation of all certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude that my faculties are true and not ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally enclined to falſehood) is abſolutely certain,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106628:6"/>and ſuch as takes away all matter of a doubt, for who can queſtion the truth of theſe aſſertions <hi>that nothing can produce it ſelf, and that from equals, if you take only equals, the remainder will be equal,</hi> both which are concluſions ariſing with the cleareſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence from that firſt principle of Science <hi>'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the ſame thing at once to be, and not be.</hi> Now ſeeing certainty conſiſts in the removal of what is or might be matter of a doubt, (for whileſt this matter of doubt remains we are not, and when 'tis once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, <hi>eo ipſo</hi> we arrive at real certainty) and ſeeing nothing can take off more then all, no certainty can be greater then that which cuts of all matter of a doubt. Nay, ſecondly, I ask, whether this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple (viz. <hi>it is impoſſible for the ſame thing at once to be and not be</hi>) can poſſibly be doubted whether ſome Concluſions Scientifical be not immediately and unavoidably derivative from it? (for ſince all Truths are ultimately reſolved into it, ſome moſt immediately conclude from it) and whether hence it will not follow, That Scientifical Concluſions may remove all poſſibility of doubting? Thirdly, all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith are ultimately founded upon Reaſon, by <hi>Prop. 2d.</hi> And ſo our aſſent unto them muſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate thereupon, no reaſon, can be of greater cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, then a Scientifical Concluſion, as being wholy derived from, and reſoluble into that firſt Principle of Science, <hi>impoſſibile eſt idem eſſe &amp; non eſſe.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That any Article of Faith is <hi>true or not true,</hi> is a Scientifical Concluſion from that of Logick <hi>one part of contradictories muſt needs be true;</hi> nor can the truth of any article be greater, then the truth of this, ſince 'tis impoſſible to be <hi>true,</hi> but <hi>eo ipſo</hi> it muſt be <hi>true or not true.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106628:6"/>
               <p>When therefore you pretend, <hi>p.</hi> 181. <hi>to cleave more heartily and firmly to a point of Faith, then to any concluſion of Science whatſoever,</hi> your adherence muſt outgoe your Reaſon, for what if <hi>Faith depend upon divine veracity, and that be cloſely applyed by the Church unto you.</hi> Seeing it depends alſo on your aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of theſe two Aſſertions, (1.) <hi>That the Divine power could not be engaged to deceive the Church, or atteſt a falſehood.</hi> Which you owe to Reaſon, And Secondly, <hi>That the divine veracity is engaged for that, which you eſteem an Article of Faith,</hi> which you muſt owe unto the Eyes and Eares and the Fidelity of other men, ſince then each Article of Faith at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by Divine Veracity is nevertheleſs known to be ſo, partly by reaſon, which cannot riſe beyond a Demonſtration, partly by the evidence of ſence, and the fidelity of other men, which is not capable of demonſtration, it is not poſſible that your aſſent which bottoms on them, ſhould exceed its cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, I affirm, that all our certitude of Faith, is leſs then that of Science, for notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all your motives unto Faith, are there not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>real Atheiſts,</hi> and ſecret <hi>rejecters</hi> of Chriſtianity? Many that are ſtill <hi>enquirers,</hi> many that labour under continual doubts, and ſcruples, and have Faith only <hi>as a grain of Muſterdſeed?</hi> Yea may we not all cry out with the Diſciples, <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith?</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce your motives, manage them with your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt care, and you will find the Sceptick will ſtill make exceptions, put in his ſcruples, and ask <hi>might it not be otherwiſe?</hi> Whereas Science compels aſſent, puts the intellect beyond a feare, and will not ſuffer us to ſcruple or demur upon her Theorems, or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106628:7"/>under the leaſt uncertainty, <hi>Whether one part of contradictories be true,</hi> or the <hi>three Angles of a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle be equal to two right ones.</hi> Sith then 'tis nothing but the clearneſs of the truth which expels fears and doubts, and 'tis the want of ſuch convictive e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which is the cauſe of their continuance, that certitude muſt needs be greateſt which is moſt effectual to this end: but 'tis ſuperfluous to inſiſt farther upon that which is ſo admirably confirmed by Mr <hi>Chillingworth, p.</hi> 291. <hi>Ed. ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea thirdly, I affirm that the certainty of Faith is not ſo great as that of ſence, for all its certainty depends on our aſſurance <hi>that the deliverers of it were infallibly aſſiſted by the Divine Wiſdome in that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> and is not this atteſted by the Miracles they wrought, the Prophecies they delivered, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine they taught? And that by ſence? Should any of them be queſtioned muſt we not recur unto the ſenſes of the Primitive Chriſtians to confirm them? And muſt they not then be the ultimate Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Faith? and your tradition? muſt we not be ſurer of the proof then the thing proved? And conſequently of the evidence of ſence then that of Faith, which deriveth from it? If not, why ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth our Lord pronounce them rather bleſſed who believe and have not ſeen, then <hi>Thomas</hi> who firſt Saw and Felt, and then Believed? Is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do it upon leſſer (though ſufficient) evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence? And ſo their Faith is more illuſtrious and prayſe worthy; 'Twould be more Generous, and Noble, to die in the defence of him whom we did only <hi>probably</hi> believe to be our <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Parent,</hi> then to do it only upon <hi>iufallible aſſurance</hi> of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch, becauſe an evidence of greater love, even
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106628:7"/>ſo is it more virtuous and prayſe worthy to venture all upon an <hi>highly probable</hi> hopes of the truth of Chriſtianity it being ſuch a <hi>pregnant indication</hi> of our true love to Pietie and Vertue, that even a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable aſſurance</hi> of it can prevail againſt all worldly temptations to the contrary: Yea this it is which rendreth Faith <hi>rewardable,</hi> that 'tis an act of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers choiſe (and not <hi>irrefragably</hi> induced) how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be abundantly confirmed with arguments <hi>extreamly probable,</hi> and ſuch as render it <hi>perverſneſs</hi> and <hi>obſtinacy</hi> to reſiſt. Thirdly ſhould it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe how cometh it to paſs that men are equally aſſured of what equally they ſee, but have not the like fulneſs of perſwaſion in what they believe? That being once aſſured of the objects of ſence, they can admit of no greater certainty, whereas after all our boaſts af a <hi>plerophory of Faith,</hi> we have ſtill need to ſtrive and labour to increaſe it? Since then the certainty of Faith is proved inferiour to that of Senſe, and Science, to pretend infallibility (which is the higheſt certainty) is to pretend ſuch evidence, as is not competible to Faith. But that the Folly of this pretence may appeare more ſignally, I ſhall farther manifeſt. 1. That Humane nature is not capable of infallible aſſurance in matters of Faith. Secondly, that to require ſuch aſſurance unto Faith is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Scripture. Thirdly, That our Saviour requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Faith upon lower motives. Fourthly, That the Romaniſts can have no ſuch aſſurance. Fifthly, That it is no prejudice to the certainty or reaſonableneſs of Faith, that it is built upon foundations not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely infallible. And Laſtly, Anſwer Mr <hi>Serjeants</hi> Exceptions to the contrary. And</p>
               <p n="1">1. If Humane Nature (abſtracted from Divinity)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106628:8"/>be capable of this aſſurance, its certainty muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to that of Viſion, of Angels, of Chriſts Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yea of God himſelf, for even their aſſurance cannot reach beyond infallibility. And ſecondly, Reaſon muſt give as great aſſurance of a thing revealed to others 1600. years agon, and in it ſelf inevident, as it is poſſible for preſent ſence or revelation to afford; all which are monſtrous abſurdities.</p>
               <p>Secondly, each Text of Scripture which mentions any that were <hi>weak</hi> or <hi>ſtrong in Faith,</hi> any that were of <hi>little</hi> or of <hi>great Faith,</hi> any that were <hi>rich,</hi> that did <hi>abound, encreaſe,</hi> or <hi>grow in Faith,</hi> any that were <hi>grounded, eſtabliſhed, rooted,</hi> and <hi>conſirmed in Faith,</hi> that ſpeakes of having <hi>Faith as a grain of muſterd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed,</hi> and of having <hi>all Faith,</hi> is a demonſtrative refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this pretence, it being certain that infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity admits of no degrees. Such ſecondly, muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Prayer which the Apoſtles made, to <hi>encreaſe</hi> their own and others <hi>Faith,</hi> or in the language of the Catholick <hi>to advance it ſome degrees above infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility.</hi> Such thirdly, are all thoſe places which tell of Hereticks, who <hi>overthrew the Faith of ſome,</hi> of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were <hi>unſtable</hi> and <hi>wavering</hi> in the Faith. And laſtly, Prophecy that men ſhould <hi>Erre,</hi> and be <hi>ſeduced from the Faith,</hi> or <hi>depart from it, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> it being as impoſſible for ſuch who are infallibly aſſured or guided by what is <hi>ſelf-evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> even to the <hi>un-reflecting perſon,</hi> to Waver, Erre, or be Seduced, as to Doubt and Disbelieve that <hi>twice</hi> 2 <hi>is</hi> 4, or <hi>that if you take equally from equals, they will ſtill be equal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Our Bleſſed Saviour required this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from his Diſciples without Infallible aſſurance, for doth he not call them <hi>Fools and ſlow of heart,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106628:8"/>Luke</hi> 24.26. for not <hi>believing all the Prophets</hi> had delivered touching his <hi>Reſurrection and Aſcention into Glory?</hi> Had they infallible aſſurance that theſe Prophecyes concerned him yea or no? If not, then did he look upon them as <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>ſlow of heart</hi> for not believing upon motives confeſſedly fallible; if their aſſurance might have been infallible, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as bottomed upon Reaſon, infallibly concluding his <hi>Aſcention</hi> and <hi>Reſurection</hi> from the Prophets; or ſecondly upon <hi>Tradition</hi> and the Churches <hi>living voice;</hi> if the firſt, why may not we alſo (who have greater aſſiſtence of the Spirit of Wiſdome) be able from the ſame Principle of Reaſon, working on our Rule of Faith, to conclude infallibly the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Chriſtianity? For is it not unreaſonable to aſſert, that the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Aſcention</hi> of our Lord is more clearly revealed in thoſe places of the Old Teſtament, (which are few, obſcure, &amp; by reaſon of the Language more ambiguous then the New, and laſtly acknowledged by the greateſt part of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Men to refer primarily to other things or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) then the Articles of our Creed are in thoſe numerous, and admirably preſpicuous places of the New Teſtament which give in Teſtimony thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? Muſt they be looked upon as Fools for not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly concluding the Aſcention of our Lord, from the obſcure <hi>items</hi> of the Prophets by the help of Reaſon? And muſt we be damned for holding Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſufficient from Scripture to conclude our Creed? Nay ſecondly, is not this to admit Reaſon as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, yea infallible judge of the Senſe of Scripture, and conſequently to approve of in the <hi>Jew,</hi> what you condemn and rail at in the <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſecondly, you flye unto Tradition, It is not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106628:9"/>ridiculous to aſſert that the Jewiſh Church ſhould not only <hi>Crucifie</hi> this Jeſus, and endeavour with their utmoſt powerto prevent the Fame of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, albeit ſhe had <hi>infallible aſſurance</hi> of it? But that ſhe ſhould at the ſame time interpret Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo, as <hi>infallibly</hi> to atteſt it, and be condemned from her own mouth? Nay had they not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Tradition, (viz. <hi>That the Kingdome of their Meſſias ſhould be Glorious upon Earth</hi>) ſufficient to confront all evidence Tradition could afford them in this caſe, and void her Teſtimony becauſe repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to it ſelf? Secondly, I deſire to know whether that voice from Heaven which teſtifyed that Jeſus was the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and the Son of God, did not oblige the hearers to believe it? And to what other end it was ſent? Whether our Saviour doth not plead it as his Fathers teſtimony of him (which ſure muſt be ſufficient ground of Faith) whether Saint <hi>Peter</hi> doth not hence endeavour to make good this truth?<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17, 18, 19.</note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whether his argument doth not oblige us to believe it? And yet whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he doth not peremptorily ſay, that 'twas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by a <hi>more ſure word of Prophecy?</hi> And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hence it doth not follow that this voice from Heaven was not an evidence moſt ſure? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not infallible; however it were ſuch as did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire belief from us, as well as them that heard it? Go now and tell your God and Saviour (what you have told our Church) <hi>That they are guilty of moſt Abſurd, Ridiculous, Irrational, Self-condemned, Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, Diabolical Tyranny, and ſuch as Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can ſcarce own, for requiring any mans aſſent to any Point or Propoſition whatſoever as evident
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106628:9"/>in Scripture, without infallible certainty,</hi> pag. 196, 198.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The Evidence which Papiſts have, or can have of any matter of Faith, is not infallible; for had they infallible Evidence to produce, is it not matter of amazement, that ſo many millions of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons endowed with Intellects as piercing, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed with all abilities which their Adverſaries can boaſt of; yea, who many of them have all temporal Motives to encline them to believe, and all the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that Papal Tyranny can inflict to awaken them into a ſerious conſideration; nay, who are Men ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly induſtrious after their ſalvation, and ſuch as know that they muſt periſh everlaſtingly, if this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be the true and onely rule of Faith which they reject: I ſay, Is it not matter of amazement, that ſuch <hi>perſons,</hi> from <hi>generation</hi> to <hi>generation,</hi> ſhould <hi>unanimouſly</hi> reject what offers it ſelf with <hi>infallible evidence</hi> and <hi>aſſurance</hi> even <hi>to the moſt rude, illiterate,</hi> and <hi>unreflecting perſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sure foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>p. 5. ſ. 10.</hi>
                  </note> that is but capable of Chriſtianity? and not onely ſo, but that they ſhould diſpute, and write Books againſt it, albeit they could never go about to do ſo, but they muſt neceſſarily be convinced infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (even as <hi>unreflecting Layicks</hi> are ſuppoſed to be) of the truth of what they thus oppoſe, which is indeed to ſay, we were, are, and (whileſt Proteſtants) muſt be as bad and obſtinate as the very <hi>Devil:</hi> This alone is abundantly ſufficient to arm the ſoul againſt all temptations unto Popery. Again, the infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your Tradition is bottomed partly upon this foundation, <hi>That your Church thinks her ſelf obliged to deliver nothing but what and ſo far as ſhe received it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106628:10"/>from the former Age and Church:</hi> But what aſſurance of this at preſent: are there not of your own Party who roundly tell us, That what<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Maldonate <hi>in</hi> Joh. <hi>6.</hi> v. <hi>53.</hi> Binius Concil: Tom: <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>624.</hi> Petavius de la penit: publ: l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7. s. 6.</hi> p. <hi>97.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>flouriſhed in the Church</hi> for many hundred of Years, is now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by her? That there was a time when the <hi>Trent</hi> deſinitions were not<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Roffenſis in confut: Lutheri, p. <hi>496. Biel</hi> in Lect: <hi>57.</hi> ſuper Canonem miſſae Durand. opuſc: <hi>15.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Scotus apud Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: de Euchar: l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>de fide,</hi> yea when the<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Vid: Potters</hi> Anſwer to charity miſtaken, <hi>pag.</hi> 73, 74.</note> 
                  <hi>contrary</hi> was delivered by the Church: That there was time when Fathers<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Non mirum eſt ſi iſti &amp; nonnulli etiam alii patres re nondum eo tempore ſatis illuftrata in eam Hareſin incidiſſent <hi>Petro Soave,</hi> Hiſt: Concil: Trident: l. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>575.</hi> Petavius in Epiphanium, p. <hi>285.</hi>
                  </note> did, and might teach contrary to what ſhe now delivers, becauſe the Church had not <hi>declared her minde:</hi> And is not this to give liberty before the definition of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, to deliver to Poſterity, even from the firſt Age to that very moment, what is flatly <hi>contradictory</hi> to the <hi>Churches voice,</hi> and to unravel the whole thread you have ſo finely ſpun.<note n="(e)" place="bottom">Bellar: l. <hi>4.</hi> de Pontif: Rom: c. <hi>14.</hi> Sec. Reſ. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis.</note> Are there not thoſe who poſitively aſſert, the definition of your Church makes that to be eſteemed a matter of Faith, which before was not <hi>neceſſarily</hi> to be deemed ſuch? who laſtly ſay, To definition of your Church is that which makes a fundamental? how many hundred times have all, or moſt of theſe things been Printed,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106628:10"/>Preached, Licenſed in your Church? and yet there is not one of them but bids defiance to your Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But ſecondly, your infallibility is bottomed upon this, <hi>That 'tis impoſſible for your Church to be deceived in judging what's Tradition.</hi> Now firſt, Is it not as certain as the truth of Chriſtianity can make it, that the whole Nation of the Jews did erre, and that moſt dangerouſly, pretending a Tradition of that nature which rendred them uncapable of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the <hi>Meſſiah?</hi> Now what was the ſad fate of theſe <hi>Traditionary Catholicks,</hi> ſcattered not onely over <hi>Jury,</hi> but through all the World? why may it not be <hi>Romes?</hi> When <hi>Arianiſm</hi> prevailed ſo much upon the World, as to fright the Orthodox Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors into <hi>Dens</hi> and <hi>Caves,</hi> when it had defiled <hi>almoſt all the World,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> (except a <hi>very few) obeyed</hi> it: Was it impoſſible in that juncture of Affairs they ſhould pretend Tradition for their Faith? doth not your<note n="(f)" place="bottom">Anſw: to <hi>Du Pleſſis,</hi> l. 2. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Cardinal Perroon,</hi> and their own Epiſtle ſhew they did?<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Epiſt. Pſeudoſynodi Aucyrans apud Epiph: <hi>p. 847.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Our Faith,</hi> ſay they, <hi>is kept as a Patrimony handed down from the Apoſtles times by their immediate Succeſſors, even to the days of our Father:</hi> And muſt that be impoſſible to the done by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which we ſee done in ſo great an inſtance? How oft did Eaſt and Weſt plead contrary Traditions, and impeach, each other for walking<note n="(h)" place="bottom">Synod: Conſt: in Trullo, Can: <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? In the beginning of the fatal breach between them, either the Plea
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106628:11"/>or Tradition was deſerted, or falſly pretended by one party; and what impoſſiblity can there be, that what happened to the one ſhould be found incident to the other? And to adde no more, Is it not<note n="(i)" place="bottom">Frequenter contingit unum Theologum conſtantiſſimè aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere ſe habere Theologicam demonſtrationem de aliquo dogmate &amp; illud deducere per evidentem conſequentiam ex ſacris literis &amp; traditionibus patrum, alium vero per oppoſitum certiſsimè affirmare ſe habere demonſtrationem Theologieam, quod illud ſit bareſis. Nec ſolum hoc contingit inter duos fingulares Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos ſed inter unam Scholam cum alterâ, <hi>Gonzales in 1 diſp. 2, 2. N. 34.</hi>
                  </note> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in the Schools to hear contrary Sects, and Parties, pretending to the Tradition of the Church of God with equal confidence? Should now the prevailing Party of a General Councel be made up of either of theſe Sects? Were it impoſſible for them to define and deliver for Tradition to Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, what they, according to their <hi>Private</hi> (but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided) Judgement eſteemed to be ſuch? Muſt it be poſſible for many handreds of <hi>Lateran</hi> or <hi>Baſil, Nice</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to pretend Tradition falſly (becauſe in contradiction to each other) and ſhall it not be poſſible for 52 Biſhops met at <hi>Trent</hi> to do ſo?</p>
               <p>But what if ſhe hath actually deceived us, Is it infallibly evident that ſhe cannot do what ſhe hath done already, and that as ſure as Hiſtory can make it? For in the ſixteenth Century, we have ſeveral Tranſlations of the Bible, ſet forth with ſpecial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces before them (ſuch were that of <hi>Santes Pagri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> the <hi>Dominician</hi> at <hi>Lyons,</hi> that of <hi>Antonius Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciolus</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi>) every one delivering, and declaring the diſtinction that we make, and was then common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiv'd, between the Canonical Books of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106628:11"/>and Apocryphal; may, in that famous Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the compleat Bibles ſet forth by <hi>Ximenius</hi> the Cardinal, and Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Toledo</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and publiſhed by the Authority of People <hi>Leo,</hi> we are told, that <hi>Tobit, Judith, Wiſdom, Eccleſiaſticus, and the Macchabes, with the additions to Heſter</hi> and <hi>Daniel, are no Canonical Scripture,</hi> but ſuch as the Church read, <hi>rather for edification of the people, then confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Faith,</hi> Yea, the vulgar Bible printed at <hi>Baſil,</hi> with <hi>Lyra</hi>'s Commentary, and the ordinary Gloſs, do not onely number her Books <hi>Canonical,</hi> and <hi>un Canonical</hi> as we do, putting that difference between them is be ween what is <hi>dubious,</hi> and what is <hi>certain;</hi> but farther tells us, That ſhe did it <hi>for the Information of them who being not much uſed to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, did not know how to put a difference betwixt them, and ſo became ridiculous to the Learned. Picus Mirandula</hi> aſſured us,<note place="margin">Admitto i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymum in ea fuiſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinione, <hi>Bellar: de verbo Dei. l. 1. c. 10.</hi>
                  </note> That the Teſtimony of St. <hi>Jerome</hi> in this matter (which pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually accords with us even our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries being Judges) <hi>was eſteemed moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred by the Church.</hi> And Cardinal <hi>Caietan</hi> (that common Oracle of the days he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in) ſaith as expreſly, <hi>What he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the Canon that do we; what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, we alſo do reject:</hi> Nay, <hi>That the Latine Church was very much obliged to S.</hi> Jerome, <hi>who by making this distinction, had freed us from the reproaches of the Jews: left them no ground to ſay of her</hi> (what now they may of the Latine Church) <hi>That ſhe had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a new Canon of her own, with which the Jews had no acquaintance:</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>Catharinus</hi> oppoſed this Sentence, as being contrary to what one or two Popes had held before him: but he was preſently
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106628:12"/>derided for it by one of his Brother Monks, as an <hi>unlearned fellow.</hi> And to conclude, <hi>Johannes Ferus,</hi> in his Book called <hi>An Examination of Perſons to be Ordained,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See this and much more in Dr. <hi>Coſens</hi>'s Canon of Scripture, <hi>Cent: 16.</hi>
                  </note> informs them of <hi>nine Apocryphal Books</hi> (the ſame which are ſo called by our Church) <hi>which were not anciently uſed in the Church,</hi> and <hi>whoſe Authority was not preſſing:</hi> To him you may adde <hi>Faber Stapulenſis, Jodochus Clictovaeus, Ludovicus Vives, Fr: Georgius, Eraſmus,</hi> and <hi>Driedo,</hi> all in this ſixteenth Century: This being ſo, Can any man imagine that the <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Authority</hi> of theſe Books was look'd upon in this Century, as an <hi>Apoſtollick Tradition</hi> by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a thing neceſſary to be taught Poſterity? and yet they are pronounced <hi>Canonical</hi> by a few Men at <hi>Trent,</hi> in the ſame Century; and a Tradition is pretended for it in defiance to their own and other Churches: If then we cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly aſſured, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> kept to Tradition when ſhe moſt pretended it (yea, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly certain, That in her firſt Decree ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted the prevailing Doctrine of that very age) What aſſurance can we reaſonably expect that ſhe always did ſo?</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>The Atteſtation of One thouſand Men of good repute, touching a matter pretended to be ſeen by them, and confirmed by their Oath, obligeth to belief: And muſt not then the Atteſtation of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>incomparably more ample, render the matter ſo indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table<hi rend="sup">c</hi> as that onely irrational, vicious, and wilfully blinde perſons can recede from it by unbelief?</hi> p. 196, 197.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106628:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> (1.) I deſire to know, Whether it were abſolutely impoſſible that One thouſand hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Phariſees ſhould have procured the repute of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men? it being Proverbial amongſt the Jews, <hi>That if Heaven were deſigned but for two perſons,</hi> the one <hi>would be a Scribe,</hi> the <hi>other a Phariſee:</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were abſolutely impoſſible for One thouſand of ſuch perſons (who were confeſſedly guilty of greater ſins, and frequently accuſtomed to ſwear a lye by any thing but the name Jehovah) to atteſt falſhood with an Oath? and if not, Why ſhould it be impoſſible to our <hi>Modern Phariſee,</hi> who can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocate as well as he? Whether the Prieſts of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polio</hi> were not many Thouſands in the World? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they might not be reputed honeſt Men? and whether it were impoſſible for them to conſent in an Atteſtation of ſuch a falſhood which might gain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to that Idol? eſpecially, conſidering that the Frauds and Artifices of the Prieſts, were the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual ways of keeping up the credit of their Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In ſome caſes ſuch a Teſtimony will oblige unto Belief: But what if theſe Witneſſes ſhould be confronted by the Teſtimony of Two thouſand equally Judicious and Pious Men? What if theſe Witneſſes ſhould very in their Teſtimonies, and when met in Councels contradict each other? What if Scripture and Hiſtory delivered to us from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Tradition of many Millions, of which this Thouſand were a part, ſhould manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them of a lye? What if the thing they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to teſtifie, depended not entirely on their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, but required alſo the Teſtimony of the next Age, and ſo up to the Apoſtles days? What if
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106628:13"/>the Atteſtation were viſibly for their own Intereſt? or they were partly ignorant of what they did At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt? Would not all or any of theſe things ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently null their evidence, and vet this is manifeſtly the caſe of your Churches Teſtimony.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, It is no ſufficient prejudice againſt the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs or certainty of Faith, to confeſs it to be built upon foundations not abſolutely infallible: This is the natural reſult of what hath been already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but 1. That it is no prejudice unto the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and reaſonableneſs of our Faith, is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded hence, That the moſt weighty Affairs of Life are built upon Foundations not abſolutely ſuch. No Childe hath an infallible aſſurance of his Parents, no Subject of his Prince; and would it not be madneſs hereupon to deny Obedience and Homage to them? our Title to our Eſtates derived from Anceſtors, our aſſurance of the Laws of the Land we live in, is but <hi>moral;</hi> nevertheleſs, to doubt or queſtion them upon this account, would be extreamly fooliſh: moreover, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Prudence oblige us to believe what is highly credible, and exceedingly more probably then it's contrary: And ſure it is, That Chriſtian Religion is upon various accounts more credible, and built on grounds incomparably more rational then either irreligion, or any contrary Religion can pretend to, and conſequently I ſtand bound in Prudence to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>But what is</hi> fallible <hi>may be</hi> falſe; <hi>and if ſo, you have no certainty that it will be true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What is fallible (not becauſe equally poyſed betwixt truth and falſhood, but) onely <hi>becauſe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable by Mathematical mediums,</hi> or becauſe the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106628:13"/>contrary doth not imply a contradiction, may yet be of ſufficient certainty to produce aſſurance: The judgement of ſenſe cannot be proved infallible to the <hi>Sceptick;</hi> he will argue from experience, That it may once or twice deceive you, and thence, that 'tis not abſolutely impoſſible that it ſhould frequently do ſo; that it may deceive you for a minute, and then ask what infallible aſſurance you can have that it cannot do ſo for five, ten, twenty minutes: If you reply, <hi>Your ſenſes are infallible, but with ſuch limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as having a due medium, Organ diſtance, and the like,</hi> he will call for your <hi>infallible aſſurance,</hi> that neither God, nor the devil, do at any time infect the <hi>Medium,</hi> diſ-tort the <hi>Eye,</hi> alter the <hi>Species,</hi> and the like. Now tell me, notwithſtanding this denyal of the infallibility of Senſe, Whether we have any juſt temptation to queſtion what we daily ſee and hear? Whether he that walls in <hi>London</hi> ſtreets may not be certain that he ſees a Man or Woman? and yet, leſs reaſon had the Primitive Chriſtians to diſtruſt thoſe Miracles which for ſome Hundreds of Years employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not onely their own Senſes, but the Eyes and Ears of all the World. Again, The teſtimony of ten, yea of an hundred Men is fallible (as we have ſeen alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;) and hence 'tis evident, That the teſtimony of Two hundred, yea a Thouſand may be ſo; for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all you adde is fallible, their Teſtification moſt be ſo: Tell me now, Whether I have reaſon to diſtruſt the Exiſtence of ſuch a Man as <hi>Alexander, Mahomet,</hi> or that the Alcoran was publiſhed by him? if not, What reaſon can I have to doubt of what's delivered to me with greater evidence of general Tradition touching Scripture &amp; Chriſtianity? you ſee now what little ground of fear our Doctrine gives you <hi>that it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106628:14"/>might happen to be otherwiſe,</hi> p. 196. becauſe we dare not pretend infallibility, even as little as you have to fear the conſtant Teſtimony of ſenſe, or your <hi>own ſure footing.</hi> And when you adde, That <hi>'tis a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and diabolical Tyranny, to oblige men to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards of falſhoods in the matters of Faith, and in the mean time, profeſs our ſelves ignorant whether they be falſe or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> True: And 'tis as great a falſhood that we do ſo. No Sir, in matters Fundamental we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs as much aſſurance as Scripture and Tradition can afford; in matters which admit not of the greateſt Evidence, we oblige not unto Faith, but to Submiſsion and Obedience; and in neither do we profeſs (what you ſo diſ-ingeniouſly impoſe upon us) That <hi>we are ignorant whether they be falſe or no.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106628:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. II.</hi> Of the Guide of Faith.</head>
               <p>THat Reaſon ſtill muſt be my guide after it hath brought me to my Rule of Faith;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> 1.</note> and were it otherwiſe (ſince we have no expreſs from the old Teſtament that <hi>Jeſus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> or the <hi>Son of Joſeph</hi> was to be the Saviour of the world) why are we ſent to Scripture to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of it? Why is this <hi>word of Prophecy</hi> eſteemed a ſurer evidence thereof then a voice from Heaven?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 5.39. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.29. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.25.</note> Why doth our Saviour quarrel with the Jew for not concluding that from Scripture which was not to be found expreſsly there? Or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the ſlowneſs; of his own Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to <hi>believe all the Prophets had delivered</hi> touching his <hi>Death, his Reſurrection, and Aſcention into Glory?</hi> When viſibly they could not do it without comparing circumſtances, and uſing a long train of inferences? Why laſtly, are the <hi>Beraeans</hi> ſo much commended for their ſearch of Scripture, &amp; Judgement of <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine thence, ſeeing his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was to prove that <hi>Chriſt muſt needs have ſuffered, &amp; be raiſed from the dead, &amp; that Jeſus was the Chriſt. Act.</hi> 17.3.11. ſhould this way be rejected as falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and unſufficient to eſtabliſh faith? In vain muſt be <hi>Apollos</hi> wiſdome endeavouring hence to convince the Jew <hi>that Jeſus was the Chriſt, Act.</hi> 18.22. And 'twas their weakneſs to be over-powred by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106628:15"/>it, whilſt he produced no expreſs from Scripture, in vain did <hi>Peter,</hi> attempt to prove the Reſurrection of our Lord from that of <hi>David, Thou wilt not leave my Soul in Hell; Act.</hi> 2.27. and S. <hi>Paul</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Jew by <hi>Reaſoning from Scripture, Act</hi> 17.2. In vain did he compoſe his whole Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> ſo full of Rational deductions thence; in a word to infer the unlawfulneſs of Divorce for any cauſe from that of <hi>Geneſis, They twain ſhall be one fleſh,</hi> of <hi>Corban</hi> from that of <hi>Moſes, Honor thy Father and thy Mother;</hi> to infer the Lawfulneſs of plucking ears of corn upon the Saboth, from <hi>Davids</hi> eating the <hi>Shew bread;</hi> And laſtly to conclude the Reſurrection from that of <hi>Moſes, I am the God of Abraham,</hi> muſt be according to the contrary Aſſertion to argue upon Grounds fallacious, and to interpret Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt or elſe beſides the tenour of the Churches voice.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If Reaſon may not be my Guide in theſe concluſions as well as others, then (1.) muſt not all Arguments produced by the Romaniſt againſt our Church, or upon any other ſubject, be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced null; when bottomed only on the inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Humane Reaſon, from the Rule of Faith, and muſt not Vanity be writ upon the labours of their greateſt Champions? Muſt it not follow that no promiſe of the Scripture, can adminiſter comfort, no threatning terror, to the Soul, that is not either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly contained in it, or otherwiſe aſcertained and expounded to us from the Tradition of the Church? And muſt not then the greateſt part of Scripture-threatnings prove <hi>bruta fulina,</hi> and its Promiſes be as unſignificative? And thirdly might not Jew, and Gentile, Sadducy, and Phariſy have ſtill exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106628:15"/>againſt Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles (whoſe infallibility they little dreamt of) for making <hi>faith</hi> depend on the fallacious deductions of their Reaſons, &amp; for moulding Scripture according to their <hi>Daedalean Phancies</hi> in oppoſition to the Churches living voice. Had Mr <hi>S.</hi> been a Traditionary Catholick or (which is much the ſame) a Phariſee in thoſe days, he would have doubly ſchoold them, (1.) <hi>For chuſing a wrong rule of Faith (viz. Scripture) ſo to avoid the Church: and next for gloſſing it as ſeems beſt unto their Reaſons and that in oppoſition to the Church: who by her practical tradition muſt interpret. Sure footing.</hi> p. 193.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. That to aſſert Reaſon as my Guide in matters of Faith, is not to reſolve Faith into humane Reaſon, for <hi>Faith is properly reſolved into its Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal efficient, or formal object,</hi> which is not Reaſon, but to the Proteſtant Divine Veracity, to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick the Churches voice for aske the Proteſtant why he believes ſuch Articles, or aſſerts their truth, he preſently replyes <hi>becauſe revealed in Scripture by that God who cannot lye;</hi> whereas the Catholick muſt Anſwer <hi>becauſe revealed by that Tradition or that Churches voice which is infallible,</hi> to aſſure me of the Churches voice is the buſineſs of my Eyes, and eares, to aſcertain me of the infallibility of that voice is the work of Reaſon; Is now the faith of Catholicks reſolved into their eyes or ears? Is it reſolved into the uſe of Reaſon, and not into the Churches voice? If not, why muſt this be objected to the Proteſtant, becauſe his Reaſon doth aſſiſt him to evince his Scripture to be the product of Divine Veracity? If then you take this prayſe in its largeſt ſenſe, as it imports the <hi>enquiry into all its cauſes in their ſeveral kinds,</hi> both Catholicks and Proteſtants do
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106628:16"/>reſolve their faith into humane Reaſon, as giving them aſſurance of the infallibility both of Scripture and Tradition, if in its proper notion as it it implyes the <hi>principal efficient cauſe of Faith,</hi> 'tis evident that neither of them do it. Nevertheleſs I freely grant that all the certainty of our Faith in things not punctually expreſſed in Scripture, depends upon the certainty of our Reaſon working upon the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſayling Rules of Logick, which as it is no diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the certainty of Faith; ſo is it a thing common unto us with Catholicks, who muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with my good Friend, <hi>That many things have been delivered by the Church which were not formally contained in her tradition or the Rule of Faith, but only thence concluded by the help of Reaſon. Sure Footing. P.</hi> 206.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. The Fundamentals of Chriſtianity (<hi>i. e.</hi> all doctrines neceſſary to the Salvation of each per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) delivered in the Rule of Faith, muſt be both evident, and obvious to the eye of Reaſon, for ſeing the proper end of a Rule is to regulate and direct, and nothing unevident, and obſcure whilſt ſuch can do that office unto thoſe, to whom it is ſo, (for this were to require the intellect to be regulated by what it cannot know to be a rule) what ever is the the Rule of Faith (and ſo of Fundamentals) muſt evidently declare them to ſuch perſons to whom it is a rule, and is it not monſtrous to imagine that God ſhould have ſuſpended our Salvation and Chriſt the very being of his Church on what's ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and void of evidence? And ſecondly ſeeing what is not obvious cannot be evident to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are unable to ſearch into the depths of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſee into the coherence of a continued train
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106628:16"/>of conſequences, that this Rule may be evident to ſuch, it muſt be obvious, Obvious I ſay in delivering the affirmative heads of Chriſtian Faith, not in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording means to extricate the underſtanding from all the Sophiſtry of a Learned Adverſary, which to require from the Rule of Faith (eſpecially as applyed to the illiterate perſon and his certainty thereof) is as abſurd, and monſtrous as to require in order to his certainty that he ſees, walks, or hears, that he ſhould have ability to Anſwer all the quirks of <hi>Zeno,</hi> and demurs of a <hi>Gaſcendus</hi> to the contrary. As therefore in theſe matters the clear and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate evidence of ſenſe is a ſufficient preſervative to the rudeſt perſon from all the Sophiſms of <hi>Zeno,</hi> and his Academy; even ſo the full and pregnant evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Fundamentals, (eſpecially if joynd with that internal evidence of the Holy Spirit which is promiſed by our Saviour to all thoſe that do his will) is ſufficient ſettlement unto the meaneſt perſon capable of Religion againſt all the Fallacies of a ſubtle Heretick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coroll.</hi> Hence I conceive it Sophiſtically objected by my Friend, <hi>That we prove and defend our Faith by skils and languages, hiſtory, and humane learning and ſo make them our Rule of Faith.</hi> For we aver the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of our Faith are ſo perſpicuouſly revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Scripture as to need no farther skill to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them, then what is neceſſary to underſtand that language in which our Rule of Faith is writ, yea what is equally neceſſary to underſtand the Churches voice which conſtantly is delivered by her repreſentatives in Greek or Latine, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the preceding skils are not of abſolute neceſſity to Faith in General, but only to ſome portions of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106628:17"/>it of which we may be ignorant without conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able prejudice to our eternal welfare; (of which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the legitimacy of Baptiſm conferr'd by Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, the <hi>Millenium</hi> &amp;c.) and if we uſe ſuch mediums in matters of the higheſt nature, we do it ſtill <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> either to conclude the ſame things from obſcurer places, which are perſpicuouſly revealed elſewhere, or to obviate the evaſions, and confute the cavils of the Hereticks, all which the Catholick doth and muſt do, both when engaged with him, and us.</p>
               <p>Thus when again he tels us, <hi>That our Rule is deal Characters, waxen-natured, and plyable to the Dedale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Phancy of the ingenious moulders of new opinions, P.</hi> 194.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis true ſome paſſages there are in it which are, &amp; may be wreſted to ſuch evil purpoſes, but ſtill the Fundamentals of our Faith are ſuch as are by no means plyable to any other ſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 4. Reaſon in judging of the ſence of Scripture is regulated partly by principles of Faith, partly by Tradition, partly by Catholick maxims of her own.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By Principles of Faith, for Scripture is to be interpreted <hi>ſecundum analogiam Fidei,</hi> that is (ſay we) particular Texts of Scripture, when dubious are ſo to be interpreted, as not to contradict the Fundamentals of Faith, or any doctrine which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and fully ſtands aſſerted in the Word of God. and <hi>2ly</hi> ſince Scripture cannot contradict it ſelf; When any Paragraph of Scripture abſolutely conſidered is ambiguous, that ſence muſt neceſſarily obtain which is repugnant to no other paragraph, againſt what may be ſo, and thus may Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106628:17"/>me in the ſence of Scripture, and what I know of it, lead me to the ſenſe of what I do not.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By tradition, for ſince tradition is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to aſſure us that there were once ſuch men as the Apoſtles who delivered that Chriſtianity, and theſe Scriptures to us which we now embrace, to queſtion the ſufficiency of the <hi>like tradition,</hi> to aſſure me of the ſence of Scripture, is virtually to call in queſtion the motives which induce us to believe it ſuch; this then would be an excellent help unto the ſence of Scripture, only the miſchief is that where it can be had, we do not want it, and where we want it 'tis but too viſible it cannot be had: Note only that I ſpeak here of a <hi>like tradition,</hi> to which two things are requiſite. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it be as general as that of Scripture. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it be ſuch as evidenceth it ſelf by Reaſon, to have been no forgery (as here it doth, it being morally impoſſible that the whole Church, in the delivery of Scripture to us, ſhould deceive or be deceived.) For the infallibility of Tradition doth not conſiſt entirely in the delivery of ſuch a Doctrine, but in the aſſurance which it gives my reaſon that it could not poſſibly have been imbraced upon other terms. The Baptiſm of Infants is at preſent (as the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating of Infants was of old) the tradition of the Church, but this gives no unqueſtionable aſſurance of the truth, or derivation of theſe cuſtoms from our Lord, and his Apoſtles, for haply the Church embraced them upon other motives; The 1. from a conceived analogy therein to Circumciſion, The <hi>2d</hi> from a miſtake of that of the Evangeliſt <hi>except you eat my fleſh &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coroll.</hi> Hence you may ſee how injurious my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106628:18"/>Friend is, in repreſenting us as rejectors of Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas we manifeſtly own it where we can have aſſurance of it, only we dare not boaſt of it, as the Papiſt doth where 'tis notoriouſly evident that both do want it, we own the conſtant not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Tradition of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corol.</hi> 2. Hence ſee the ſtability of the Faith of Proteſtants above that of Papiſts: The Proteſtant firſt denyes the Tradition which the Catholick pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to, to be ſufficient ground of Faith; And <hi>2dly,</hi> he denyes the Articles of his Faith to have the leaſt <hi>Sure-footing</hi> in Tradition, or his rule of Faith nay proves them wholy oppoſite unto it; the Papiſt doth acknowledge that even by his own, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtants Rule of Faith, muſt be infallibly certain, and pronounceth her Anathema, upon all who do not own both Scripture and Tradition for infallible, and receive them both <hi>pari pietatis affectu,</hi> with the like pious affection, as the <hi>Trent Council</hi> phraſeth it, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 4. The Papiſts Faith is not to be found in the Proteſtants Rule of Scripture, and this neceſſitates him to flie unto Tradition, but the Proteſtants Creed and all his fundamentals are confeſſedly cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from the Papiſts Rule; if therefore prudence doth direct us to the ſafer way, and that be ſuch which both ſides do agree upon, (which they ſo frequently inſiſt on to pervert the people) it muſt be every mans concern to be a (Proteſtant rather then a Papiſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Reaſon is herein guided by her prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Maxims, and cannot rationally admit of any thing as the ſenſe of Scripture, which is apparently repugnant to them; for ſeeing 'tis impoſſible to yield a rational aſſent without reaſon, it muſt be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106628:18"/>more impoſſible to do it againſt reaſon. Beſides, right Reaſon muſt be true, and therefore ſhould a Revelation be manifeſtly repugnant unto right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it muſt equally be oppoſed to truth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Do we not all endeavor to give Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our Faith? Would we not all be thought to follow it, when we conclude our Faith from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture or Tradition? Should we renounce her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, might not the worſt abſurditys be imbraced as the ſenſe of Scripture, and finde their Patrimony from thence, without all fear of refutation from that Reaſon, which muſt not be admitted to diſpute its ſenſe? muſt it not follow, That no Controverſie could be determined, no Diſpute reſolved, no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt about the ſenſe of Scripture finde an iſſue from any rational procedure?</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>But doth not the Myſtery of the Sacred Trinity, the Reſurrection of the Body, the Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, ſpeak Contradictions unto Humane Reaſon? Why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do you not expunge them from among the Articles of your Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Theſe things, as far as Scripture doth aſſert them, are lyable to no immediate Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but if your Curioſity proceed to dive into the Modes of their Exiſtence, you will preſently diſcourſe your ſelf into perplexing Difficulties, not in theſe onely, but moſt other Matters: That God is omnipreſent, ſpeaks no contradiction to my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but to enquire into the Modus of this Preſence, is to be loſt in mazes of them: That he hath infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Duration, is a neceſſary truth; but to call this Duration momentaneous or ſucceſſive, is to lay a foundation for endleſs Contradictions; to aſſert Gods Omniſcience, is to aſſert a moſt received Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106628:19"/>of our Faith, but how this knowledge can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the contingency of things, is beyond hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmity to ſhew, that there is ſuch a thing as motion we all ſee, but whether it be a mode, quality, or ſubſtance, ſucceſsive only, or inſtantane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, continued or intermixt with morula's, needs an <hi>Elias</hi> to reſolve us; that there is quantity and corporeal Beings in the world, our ſenſes can aſſure us, but how their parts are knit unto each other, and how far they may be divided, is indeed a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophick Trinity, 'tis then no prejudice to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Articles, that we may diſcourſe them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contradictions, ſince this is common to them, with the moſt ordinary things our ſenſes view, the reaſon of theſe perplexing difficulties in matters of this nature, may happily be the exceeding great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or parvitude of the thing, which renders it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible for us to frame Ideas of them, from any thing which occurs unto our ſenſes; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to paſs judgment on them, thus all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties both of quantity and motion are bottomed upon inſtants and indiviſibles, and that which gravels ſtill the mind in the conſideration of a Deity, is the infinity of his nature, and therefore theſe affections of Goodneſs, Wiſdome, and Mercy &amp;c. Which we ſtile communicable, when once infinity is annexed to them, do as much be jade the intellect, as that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing myſtery of the holy Trinity; but ſecondly, I anſwer,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. That Reaſon cannot think it proper to apply her maxims to theſe inſtances, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cannot judge them repugnant thereunto. This will appear from theſe concluſions,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Reaſon Guided by her own maxims,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106628:19"/>Tradition and by Scripture, aſſures me that the divine nature is incomprehenſible, it being impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that what is finite ſhould comprehend what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and certainly if Mathematicks have her Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes, and can vie demonſtrations <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> if matters obvious to ſence do ſo be jade the intellect, and lock it up in contradictions, 'tis little to be hoped ſhe ſhould conveigh her ſelf through the infinite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſs of of divine perfections, and not ſuffer ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That infinite perfection may deliver ſuch things of it ſelf which are incomprehenſible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may deliver what in it ſelf it is.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That Reaſon cannot pretend to judge by her own maxims, of the Truth or Falſehood of what ſhe doth acknowledge to exceed her reach; For ſure ſhe cannot reaſonably pretend to know what thus exceeds her knowledge, much leſs to judge of what ſhe doth not know?</p>
               <p n="4">4. That Reaſon cannot conclude that to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to her maxims which ſhe acknowledgeth to be ſuch of which her maxims cannot judge, for this is to apply theſe maxims where they ought not to be applyed, and to frame conſequences upon terms whereby the things they ſignifie are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and in effect to reject the proportions of the Sun and Stars unto the Earth, which Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks gives us as repugnant to the ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That notwithſtanding this, Reaſon doth force me to attribute to God all that is perfection, and remove the contrary, he being therefore incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible becauſe infinite in perfection, whence albeit I do not comprehend his nature, yet can I rationally conclude him not corporeal, becauſe that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106628:20"/>neceſſarily ſubjects him to varietie of imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This doth not prejudice the uſe of Reaſon in other matters, any more then the Aſymptoticks of the Mathematicks, the <hi>cruces logicorum,</hi> the <hi>Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubilia</hi> of other ſciences do prejudice our getting knowledge in theſe matters, by the uſe of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corol.</hi> Hence evident it is, That Scripture muſt not alwaies be interpreted according to the Letter, or Grammatical importance of the words, becauſe that often is contradictory both to reaſon, tradition, and the Analogie of Faith, this cannot be diſputed by any perſon who is not profeſſedly induſtrious to render Scripture odious and ridiculous, there being nothing more abhorrent from humane nature then ſome Scriptures are in their Grammaticall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but you object,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob. If Reaſon muſt guide you ſometimes ſo as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the clear letter of Scripture</hi> (or to deny the Spouſe of Chriſt, is properly whatever ſhe is ſtiled in the Canticles) <hi>by what principles muſt Reaſon be regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this enquiry, Whether God hath hands and feet, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 193.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. By Principles of Faith, or thoſe perſpicuous Scriptures, which dogmatically aver that <hi>he is a Spirit inviſible, and without all ſhape,</hi> &amp; laſtly, attribute unto him many things repugnant to a body, &amp; this you ſee is done <hi>antecedently to the known ſence of ſome Scriptures,</hi> though not of all. And 2. by Reaſon, aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me that corporeity is incompatible with that power, which is every where infinite: That it is an imperfection, and ſo not incident to this all-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Being; that it interferes with his ſimplicity and independance, degrades him beneath the ranke of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106628:20"/>Angels, and humane Souls, which Scriptures repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as incorporeal, that to aſcribe ſuch Phraſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly unto him, muſt repreſent him the worſt of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (as having wings and ſeaven eyes, and putting on more ſhapes then ever <hi>Proteus</hi> did) and render his reproofs of Heathen Images irrational and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>But is not this to flie back for refuge to the old rule Humane Reaſon, which you ſeemingly renounced when you had found your new Rule of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Its power to paſs judgement of the truth of what is revealed in Scripture I did, and do renounce, its aſsiſtance in finding out the ſence of Scripture, I cannot renounce without the ſorfeiture of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corol.</hi> 2. Hence it muſt follow, that to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly contained in Scripture, is not to be the mind of God contained in Scripture, for that God is a <hi>Shepheard</hi> and a <hi>Roaring Lyon,</hi> a <hi>Lanthorn,</hi> and a <hi>wall of fire,</hi> that he begat <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and doth continue to <hi>beget</hi> Believers. That the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is a <hi>Lamb,</hi> a <hi>Lyon,</hi> and a <hi>Stag,</hi> a <hi>Worm, Plant, Fagle, Root,</hi> and <hi>Cedar,</hi> this and much more is expreſsly told us from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures letter, but to infer hence that Reaſon guided by Scripture cannot otherwiſe interpret them but it muſt <hi>Violently wreſt</hi> the Scripture, <hi>and be ſo abſolutely the Rule of Faith, as to controle and baffle Scripture though clearly revealing, p.</hi> 192. is to make Chriſt the worſt of Monſters, to out do all the Fables of the Poets, and repreſent the God of Heaven more ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous then an Heathen <hi>Jupiter.</hi> Secondly, I defire to know whether the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth own and ſence theſe places according to the letter, or <hi>contradict and wreſt, baffle and controul the cleareſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106628:21"/>of the word of God</hi> by doing otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. But if to be in expreſs terms in Scripture, be not to be clearly revealed there, what is it to be thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Tis manifeſtly to be the mind of God contained in Scripture.</hi> Which being ſo if you continue to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that every thing contained in Scriptures letters, is clearly manifeſted to be the mind of God in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then muſt you either contradict what is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted ſo to be, or cut off hands, and feet, and pluck out eyes, that you may be Chriſts Diſciple: if you enquire farther amidſt all the varietie of Tropes and Figurative Expreſſions uſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how any thing can be manifeſted to be the mind of God revealed: I Anſwer, by the very ſame means and circumſtances, by which we know the mind of one another, notwihſtanding all the variety of Tropes and Figures, which we uſe in ordinary Diſcourſe or Writing, how often doth the Divine, the Poet, the Hiſtorian, and eſpecially the Orator flouriſh in all the arts of Rhetorick, and Grace his ſubject with the chioſeſt flowers of Eloquence, and yet preſents it in a dreſs as clear, as it is pleaſant, and were not men wilfully perverſe, they would have leſs reaſon to complain of the obſcurity of the Scripture in matters neceſſary to Salvation, upon this account.</p>
               <p>When therefore you thus Argue, <hi>That God hath Hands, Feet, Noſtrils, is plainly writ in your Rule of Faith, p.</hi> 121. and therefore is revealed in it; the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence muſt be weak, &amp; the Foundations of it are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready overturned. And yet however you ſuppoſe it, all along, I peremptorily deny that it is poſsitively aſſerted in any Scripture, that God hath Hands,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106628:21"/>Feet, Noſtrils. True, we are told the Heavens are the Workmanſhip of his hands &amp;c. But to infer it from ſuch places would force you to acknowledge that the Word of God is Milk, and that Milk is Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, becauſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſtiled it <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Here therefore is no need to <hi>captivate my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> much leſs to Anſwer as you would have me, <hi>That the contrary is plain in Scripture too, pag.</hi> 191. and ſo that Scripture holds forth plainly contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, this Anſwer ſo diſhonourable to God and Scripture, ſo repugnant unto Faith, Reaſon and Tradition I permit to be your own.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106628:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Rule of Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop:</hi> 1. SEeing Divine Faith, in the proper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the words, is <hi>an aſſent to Divine Authority revealed,</hi> whatever I aſſent to, as an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith, I muſt aſſent to as being the revealed will of God; whence evident it is, That the mind or will of God revealed, and nothing elſe, muſt be my Rule of Faith. Again, What is the proper office of a Rule, but to examine what is to be ruled by it? Muſt we not paſs a Judgement on our Weights and Meaſures, by bringing them to the Rule and Standard? In like manner, Do we not examine each Theological concluſion by this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, Whether it be the minde of God revealed or not, and from the Anſwer made unto it, paſs Judgement on the thing in Queſtion? This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the Rule of every Theological concluſion: And ſo of Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corol.</hi> 1. Hence it will follow, That not Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the minde of God revealed in Scripture, or Tradition, is the Rule of Faith: And indeed, Tradition (where it as certain as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſuppoſeth it) would be the formal Object, but not the Rule of Faith, which two things are miſerably confounded through the whole Series of my Friends Diſcourſe, as will appear from the diſtinctive Characters of them both, as they are excellently given us in the Learned Baron, <hi>Apoll: p.</hi> 34. S. 6.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, A Rule is that Exemplar by which the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106628:22"/>minde is regulated, and to which it ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable; and ſo the Rule of Faith is that Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar which we ought to follow, and conform unto in Matters of Faith: Now ſuch apparently is the mind of God revealed in general, nor is the voice of Chriſt, or of Tradition ſuch, but on preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption that they are the minde of God revealed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Rule doth limit, and determine what is ruled by it; even ſo the Rule of Faith muſt fix the Bounds of Faith, inſtructing us what and how many are the material Objects of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The effect of the Rule of Faith, is that knowledge which preceeds the act of Faith; for it informs the Intellect, by propoſing to it what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to be believed, but not evincing it to be ſuch.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The Rule of Faith is onely a compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive Syſteme of all the Articles of Faith, as the Rules of Grammer are a comprehenſive Syſteme of ſuch things as are to be obſerved in compoſing La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Greek, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now all theſe things do viſibly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree unto the minde of God revealed, but are as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly inconſiſtent with Tradition, as it imports <hi>a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very down from hand to hand of the ſence and Faith of Fathers to their Children;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sure foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, p. 41.</note> for, not the Tradition, but the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum,</hi> or Faith delivered is the minde of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and conſequently the Rule of Faith. But now the formal Object is that which cauſeth us to believe the Rule of Faith; and in my Friends ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>applys with certainty Divine Authority to my underſtanding,</hi> p. 181. which ſure is the pretended buſineſs of <hi>Tradition,</hi> and the whole intendment of <hi>ſure footing</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:106628:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cor:</hi> 2. Hence evident it is, That <hi>Scriptures Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> as abſtracted from the ſenſe included, cannot poſſibly be the Rule of Faith, becauſe, as ſuch, it cannot be the minde of God revealed: and when my Friend concludes, <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>We cannot own the ſenſe or things contained in Scripture for the Rule of Faith, becauſe they are the very Points of Faith, of which the Rule of Faith is to aſcertain us:</hi> He gives a pregnant Inſtance of that ignorance of the term I charge him with, for evident it is from what we have diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, That the Rule of Faith is onely a Collection of the Points of Faith, and that its buſineſs is not to aſcertain, but propound what is aſcertain'd by the formal Object; nay, may I not conclude with parity of Reaſon, that the Churches voice, abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the ſignification or import of it is to the Catholick the Rule of Faith, becauſe the matters ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by that voice are the very Points of Faith of which the Churches voice is to aſcertain us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corol:</hi> 3. Hence we may rectifie theſe looſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of the Rule of Faith, ſo frequent in the Animadverſions of Mr. <hi>S.</hi> thus when he asks, <hi>p.</hi> 188. <hi>Is not that ſpeaking formally and properly the Rule of Faith, which gives us Chriſts ſenſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is indeed the Rule of Faith, which gives Chriſts ſenſe ſubjectively, ſo as to contain, and be the minde of Chriſt revealed in Scripture, not that which gives it, onely by declaring the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the words in which this ſence is cloathed; for then each Pamphlet of this nature muſt be a Rule of Faith unto the Reader, each Maſs Prieſt to the illiterate Papiſt, each <hi>Nomenclator, Poſtiller,</hi> and Comment to the Maſs-Prieſt as oft as they explain unto him the ſence and meaning of his Rule of Faith.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106628:23"/>Thus when again we are intreated to conſider, <hi>That a Rule to ſuch an effect, is the immediate knowledge to the power as converſant about the effect, p.</hi> 190. From what hath been delivered we conclude ſuch knowledge, cannot be the rule but the effect thereof (even as my skil in making ſyllogiſms is the effect of <hi>logick rules</hi>) <hi>V.G.</hi> I doubt of ſuch a truth, put caſe the Divinity of Chriſt, the effect is conviction, the mind of God revealed in Scripture is my <hi>rule,</hi> this <hi>rule</hi> informs my knowledge, &amp; that knowledge produceth the aſſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. Hence evident it is that neither Reaſon, nor skill in Arts or Sciences is made our Rule of Faith, becauſe we do not look upon them as the mind of God revealed, or any part thereof. 'Tis true my Friend endeavours to faſten this upon us, but by ſuch <hi>mediums</hi> as ſhew too evidently he was not well acquainted with the terms he uſed. And firſt, That Reaſon and its Maxims are our Rule of Faith, he thus endeavours to conclude: <hi>p.</hi> 190. <hi>He that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth muſt have ſome principles in his head by which he is regulated in making ſuch a judgement, thoſe principles then muſt be his Rule in that action, and if that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be an adhaeſion to the point of Faith</hi> (that is if the cauſe be the effect, for no man adhers to any point of Faith, till he hath judg'd it to be ſuch) <hi>theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are his Rule of Faith; now do not Proteſtants oft conclude the ſence of Scripture from maxims of their Humane Reaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> (Beſides the blunder which my Parentheſis takes notice of) we have a greater weakneſs in this Argument: For it ſuppoſeth all by which my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is aſsiſted in determining of what is Faith, or finding out the ſence of any Scripture to be my Rule of Faith. (and therefore is as effectual to perſwade
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106628:24"/>the <hi>Galleniſt</hi> his skill in Greek, is his Rule for Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, as inabling him to finde out certainly the rules of <hi>Galen</hi>) whereas to be the Rule of Faith is a thing proper to theſe Principles, which contain the material Objects of Faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I deſire to know whether your conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Diſputes (managed by Maxims of your private Reaſon) touching the ſence of almoſt every Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the <hi>Trent,</hi> and other Councels, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions you embrace as the Churches voice, do not plainly manifeſt the Maxims of Reaſon to be as much your Rule as ours?</p>
               <p>And thirdly, Whether what was ſufficient to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Faith in me, and upon which its certainty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends entirely, may not ſufficiently aſſure me of one particular Object of it?</p>
               <p>Secondly, That skill in Arts and Sciences, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and Hiſtory, are made our Rules of Faith, is concluded from a double Argument.</p>
               <p>Obj: 1. <hi>That in Diſputes againſt them, we prove and defend our Faith by ſuch skills as Language, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and other Knowledge got by humane Learning, and conſequently hold it upon the Tenure of theſe Skills, which therefore are our Rule of Faith.</hi> p. 190.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a very formidable Argument, and muſt force you to confeſs, That in proving and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of your Faith againſt us Proteſtants, you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhew your skill in Hiſtory, or any other part of humane Learning, or to acknowledge (what you ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor ſo much, <hi>p.</hi> 188.) that theſe alſo are your Rules of Faith: Should a <hi>Jew, Socinian,</hi> or <hi>Pagan,</hi> uſe this very Argument againſt your Church, I wonder how you would avoid the blow?</p>
               <p>Secondly, Your next Aſſault runs thus: <hi>Do not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106628:24"/>theſe Skills clear the letter of Scripture; that is, make known Gods ſence to you? if ſo, ſince their immediate effect is to clear it, 'tis impoſſible to deny but they are at leaſt part of the Revelation</hi> (as if it were impoſſible to deny the Comment to be a part of that Text it cleareth) <hi>for revealing is clearing; and Gods ſenſe was not clearly revealed but by theſe means, that is, by humane Maxims, and ſo they are at leaſt the more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal part of your Rule of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I remember when I learn'd my Grammer, that I had a Conſtruing Book, the immediate effect of which, was to clear to me the ſence of my Rules co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain'd in <hi>Propria quae maribus, Quae Genus, &amp;c.</hi> but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was I ſo happy as to know that my <hi>Conſtruing book</hi> was part of them, or to which ſpecial Rule it did belong: I knew indeed <hi>that revealing was clearing,</hi> and that the ſence of theſe ſpecial Rules was not clearly revealed to me, but by means of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing Book; but was not ſo <hi>inured to Science,</hi> and <hi>verſed in true Logick,</hi> as to be able to infer thence, That it was at leaſt the moſt formal part of the Rules forementioned, but muſt thank my Friend for his Inſtruction in ſo deep a Myſtery, and confeſs I owe that Light I have received in this Point, to his <hi>noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Sun of ſelf-evidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For a cloſe you ask, <hi>Might I not have miſtaken the true ſenſe of Scripture without theſe humane Maxims? if ſo, then they, not Scriptures-letter, are my Rule of Faith. p.</hi> 191.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And muſt that neceſſarily be my Rule of Faith, without which I might poſſibly have miſtaken any portion of it? then good Eyes, and Ears, and diligence in uſing of them; good Diſpoſitions, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Inſtruction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt be my Rule of Faith;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106628:25"/>for without theſe, 'tis very probable I may be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently miſtaken in the ſenſe thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. That notwithſtanding any thing M. <hi>S.</hi> hath pleaded to the contrary, Scripture may be a Rule of Faith, for to object, <q rend="inline">That Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had deſcended many ſteps ere the Scriptures parts were much ſcattered, much leſs the whole collected,</q> is effect to argue thus, Scripture was not a Rule to thoſe that wanted, and therefore cannot be ſuch unto thoſe that have it: 'twas not the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rule to thoſe who were aſſiſted by the infallible guidance of the Authors and Propounders of it, graced with the extraordinary aſſiſtance of the ſame Spirit, who drank even from the Fountain and Spring-head of Tradition, and therefore it cannot be ſo to us who are removed from it 16 Centuries, and deſtitute of all thoſe Priviledges and Advantages which they enjoyed: And yet remarkable it is, That amidſt all theſe Enjoyments the new-born Chriſtian is ſent unto his Scripture Rule; his word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, bid to give heed unto it as a thing more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain then a voice from Heaven, writ deſignedly for his inſtruction, able to make his wiſe unto ſalvation, perfect both in Faith and Manners, and make him throughly furniſhed unto all good Works: and after all, the Apoſtles are inſpired to indite and to deliver the New Teſtament unto them to be the pillar and the ground of Faith; and can it be imagined that Scriptures ſo comparatively obſcure, ſo purpoſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for, and accommodated to the Jewiſh Paeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogy, ſhould be thus commended and enjoyned by the Spirit of God as a Rule unto the Chriſtian, when graced with all the helps fore-mentioned; and yet that Scripture which was indited by the ſame uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106628:25"/>Spirit, in a more familiar way <hi>with great plainneſs of</hi> ſpeech,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12, 13.</note> and not obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>by a vail, as was that of Moſes,</hi> which is exceedingly more full of moral Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Rules of Faith and Manners, of gracious Promiſes to comfort, and Exhortations to perſwade to Patience and every other Vertue; which laſtly, was Indited not in a Tongue peculiar to the Land of Jury, but ſuch as was moſt generally ſpoken throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the World, ſhould never be intended as a Rule unto them, when deſtitute of thoſe aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</p>
               <p>Obj: 2. <hi>'Tis objected ſecondly, That that can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be a Rule which many follow, and yet their thoughts ſtraggle into many ſeveral Judgements in Points of ſo great moment as the Trinity. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you imagine that theſe ſtraglers do indeed keep cloſe unto the minde of God revealed in Scripture, you blaſpheme the Holy Ghoſt, and make the Word of God the very ſourſe of Hereſie: if you affirm that cannot be a Rule which ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to follow, you in effect aſſert the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and right Reaſon could not be the Gentiles rule, and that he had no <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s to guide him to the knowledge of the Being and Attributes of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they generally took up with ſuch uncouth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and groſs abſurdities in matters which are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the light of Reaſon: That neither Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture nor Tradition could be a Rule unto the Jew, who branched into ſuch Sects, as either did evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Law of God by their Traditions, or deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Reſurrection: That Tradition is no Rule of Faith; or otherwiſe, That no pretender to it was ever guilty of an Hereſie, And laſtly, That the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106628:26"/>of Tradition muſt be the onely Hereſie; all which are monſtrous Abſurdities, and yet the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reſults of your Aſſertion.</p>
               <p>To conclude this Section, I muſt crave leave to minde my Friend of an early brood of <hi>Carpocratian</hi> Hereticks, who being confounded by the Scriptures to be revenged of them gave it out,<note place="margin">Cum ex Scripturis arguuntur in accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem convertantur ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum Scripturarum, quaſi non rectè habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, neque ſint ex au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate, dy quia va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſunt dictae &amp; quia non poſsit ex his inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niri veritas, ab his, qui neſciunt traditionem, non enim per literas traditam illam, ſed per vivam vocem Iren. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> (1.) <hi>That they were not as they ſhould be (viz.</hi> the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal copies being not preſerved entire <hi>Diſc.</hi> 2. <hi>S.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.) <hi>had not authority ſufficient</hi> (there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no means to <hi>convince the Sceptick,</hi> the <hi>acute Adverſary,</hi> yea the <hi>rational doubter</hi> of their trath, no <hi>certainty</hi> of Scripture in it ſelf and no <hi>aſcertableneſs</hi> of it unto as <hi>Diſc.</hi> 4. <hi>S.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) And (3) <hi>That they were ſpoken variouſly</hi> (or ſo as to admit of diverſe ſences, <hi>Diſc.</hi> 2. <hi>S.</hi> 6.8.) And laſtly, <hi>That in them the truth could not be found by ſuch a were ignorant of Tradition, it being not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by writing but by oral Tradition.</hi> Good <hi>Sir,</hi> I do not in the leaſt ſuſpect that you have Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocratians Manuſcript, or that this paſſage of the Father did ſupply you with the heads of your Diſcourſe, however it will let you ſee <hi>that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres firm to your Rule, p.</hi> 589. If then your inference ſtand good, the Carpocratian muſt be owned for your Brother Catholick, if bad, then bluſh hereafter to conclude our union with <hi>Socinus,</hi> becauſe we both acknowledge the ſame Rule of Faith.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106628:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. That the Churches voice or practical Tradition is not neceſſary to acquaint us with the ſence of Scripture as my Friend would have it, for if ſo (1.) Scripture muſt be in vain delivered to us: for where I have the ſuffrage of infallible Tradition I cannot want it, where I want that I cannot have it. (2.) In vain are all the Comments of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for where Tradition is ſilent they want a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rule to go by, and therefore muſt be ſilent to, or ſpeak at all adventures, and where ſhe ſpeaks her evidence is ſuch as rendreth all their pains ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous. (3.) All Arguments from Scripture muſt be vain whether intended to convince the Heretick, or your brother Catholick, if you contend againſt your Brother Heretick from Scripture, he preſently demands whence have you your aſſurance of that ſence of Scripture which you plead for, if you reply from the <hi>tradition</hi> of your Church, he laughs to hear you beg the Queſtion, if from any other <hi>Medium,</hi> he preſently returns upon you is it certain yea, or no? If not, then may it haply deceive him, if ſo, then do you act the Proteſtant, and own ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certain Guide unto the ſence of Scripture then that of practical Tradition; 'tis vain alſo to diſpute from Scripture with your Brother Chatholick, for if you have no practical Tradition to aſſure you of the ſence of Scripture you have no <hi>Medium</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him by, if you have practical Tradition 'tis <hi>ſelf-evident,</hi> and conſequently cannot be matter of diſpute or queſtion'd by your Brother Traditors whileſt ſuch, whence it muſt neceſſarily follow that all the <hi>School Diſputes,</hi> &amp; all endeavours of your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catholick, to decide a controverſy from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt be in vain, all their <hi>arguments</hi> from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106628:27"/>precarious, and all their pretenſions to Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in theſe matters wilful cheats: if this be not ſufficient, let me farther ask whether all moral du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties compriſed in Scripture may be interpreted by Tradition: if not, whether they be not uſeleſs to us; if ſo whether the Jeſuits and <hi>Italian</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold no Doctrines inconſiſtent with them, or whether that can be eſteemed the Tradition of the Church which is ſuppoſed by ſo great and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Members of it? Whether theſe were the only means and meaſures of interpretation to the Jewiſh Church, if not, how came they to be needful to the Chriſtian, whoſe Rule is much the clearer, and whoſe aſſiſtance from that Spirit which leadeth unto truth far greater? If ſo, then let us brand our Saviour for a Malefactor, and pronounce with them that by their Law he ought to dye, let us reject his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as being wholy Spiritual, and therefore oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to what Tradition taught them to expect, let us reject his Law, as cancelling and diſſolving that of <hi>Moſes</hi> which they pronounced eternal: yea laſtly, let us impeach the Arguments of Chriſt, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles as not only wanting this Authentick <hi>medium</hi> to arrive at the ſence of Scripture, but being manifeſtly repugnant thereunto, or at leaſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire at the ſtupidity of the Scribes and Phariſees, who (albeit they ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair) ſhould neither plead this in their own behalf, nor accuſe our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or his Apoſtles for their pragmatical oppoſition to it, but this argument is ſo copious, and the dream ſo entirely Beameniſtical, that I ſhall not upbraid the Readers underſtanding by its farther refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:106628:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 4. Tradition is not the only Rule of Faith, for if ſo, the Church muſt lye expoſed to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perils, and want a rule of Faith in matters of the higheſt moment. For if Tradition be the ſole Rule of Faith,</p>
               <p>Firſt, certain it is, that where we want Tradition, we muſt want the Rule of Faith, and conſequently muſt waver, and be undetermined in all theſe inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and caſes in which Tradition proves ſilent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis manifeſt that what is eagerly maintained, and practiſed by many thouſand Romiſh Proſelites, aſſerted by whole Sects and Orders of their Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt men, what paſſeth daily uncontrouled both from Preſs and Pulpit, as having nothing contrary to the Churches Doctrine, and the Rule of Faith, nay is acknowledged to be ſuch by thoſe who vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently oppoſe it, what laſtly doth not render the Abettors of it, how numerous ſoever, guilty of an Hereſie, nor ſubject them to the cenſure of the Church, cannot interfere with the Tradition of the Church, or be condemned by it, or if ſo Tradition cannot be ſelf-evident, as my Friend would have it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly evident it is that many poſitions of this nature are ſtifly canvaſed in the Schools, many ſuch practiſes uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed and practiſed, muſt expoſe the Soul to the greateſt peril in matters of the higheſt moment: For inſtance,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Therefore they lye open to the peril of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, or exceſſive Rule of Faith, for what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance can they have whether the definition of the Pope alone, or in conjunction with his Cardinals be the infallible guide of Faith, or whether this be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106628:28"/>the peculiar buſineſs of a Council, and whether this infallibility reſpect ſubſtantials only, or circumſtances, Faith or Fact, the concluſion only, or the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; whether it reſt upon the due proceedings of the Council, the Confirmation of the Pope, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent approbation of the Church, or be wholly independant on them, whether the Tradition of the preſent Church be indeed a Rule, or only ſuch Traditions, which can extrinſically be proved Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall, whether this Tradition be a total, or a partial Rule, and what are the infallible Criterions of it; theſe things are hotly conteſted in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore cannot be defined by her Tradition, what remains then but that each ſoul lye open to the peril of a falſe defective, or exceſſive, yea contradictory Rule of Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They lie expoſed to the peril either of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and Idolatry on the one hand, or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge on the other: for (to omit their infinite diviſions about the Worſhip due to Saints, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the Bleſſed Virgin, the Veneration due to Reliques, the sacrament, and its appendages, and touch only upon that of Images) they are altogether uncertain whether they ought to pay their homage to the image or before it only, (which is aſſerted by ſome few, though cenſured by their expurgatory Indexes) whether this Homage muſt be <hi>dulia</hi> or <hi>latria,</hi> and if ſo, whether abſolute, and ſimple, or only Analogically ſo called, whether all or any part of this pretended worſhip be due unto the image abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conſidered, or only relatively, as it refers to that of which tis an Image, in theſe matters to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient is preſently to be Sacrilegious, by robbing the Image of that honour which is due unto it, to exceed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106628:28"/>is to be guilty of Superſtition, or Idolary, by giving it that Homage which belongs not to it, and how to fleer my courſe ſo as not daſh on either of theſe rocks Tradition cannot poſſibly aſſiſt me.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt be inſmitely uncertain in matters of obedience to God. For ſeeing 'tis as evident as the Sun, and lately manifeſted by <hi>Montalius</hi> (a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick) that the Doctrines of the Jeſuited Papiſt touching Repentance, Good intentions, the Love of God, &amp;c. do cut the ſinews of all virtue, and null the precepts of true pietie, and equally certain, that they are maintained by the graveſt Doctors of their Church, nay ſtyled the common Doctrine of the Church, is follows that they interfere not with their Rule of Faith and therefore cannot be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by it.</p>
               <p n="4">4, They muſt be deſtitute of all the preſervatives againſt the vileſt of Rebellions, it being frequently aſſerted in the Schools and held by moſt confider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able members of that Church, that Catholicks may be abſolved from their Oaths, Vows, and Covenants made to Princes, and authorized by his Holineſs to depoſe them. From what hath been diſcourſed, it muſt follow that if Tradition be the only Rule of Faith: then</p>
               <p n="1">1. Should Catholicks act up to the moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate conſequences of ſuch opinions which paſs thus currant in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be condemned by or rationally be ſaid to devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate from her Rule of Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the vileſt Chriſtian and worſt of Subjects may do all that Catholick Religion, and his duty doth oblige him too, becauſe all that practical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or the Churches living voice requires; that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106628:29"/>what is ſtrangely oppoſite and ſcandalous to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and deſtructive unto Civil Government is yet aſſiſtent with their Rule of Faith, and that 'tis law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to opine at pleaſure in theſe matters.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That theſe diſeaſes muſt be all incurable, and admit of no redreſs for to make them paſs into Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and improve themſelves into articles of Faith, is to impower the Church to coyn new ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and pretend Tradition where it is not to be had.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That what ever hath been ſaid of ſome doth equally proceed againſt all other ſcandalous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Church, of which nature 'twere eaſie to collect ſufficient to tire mine own, and the Readers patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106628:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. IV.</hi> Of the Authority of the Church in matters of Faith.</head>
               <p>THAT the Church is a Society,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> 1.</note> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name, and notorelty of the thing, the definition, members, diſcipline, and conſtitutions of it do ſufficiently declare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. That this ſociety muſt be inveſted with a Ruling power, is certain, both from the nature of all Civil union, which implyes a compact, and that a Governour, whoſe buſineſs it is, to ſee that they who enter into compact, do not violate the lawes thereof, as alſo from the ends of this Society, <hi>viz.</hi> The union and due ordering of her Members and execution of her diſcipline to the correction, or excluſion of ſuch perſons who cooperate towards her ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. The Church is a Society of Believers, or of men united in the belief of certain Articles, as the Foundations of it, hence ſtyled fundamental Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, this is the joynt conſent of Chriſtians, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in the notion and number of their fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals they differ much.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corol.</hi> Hence it muſt follow that Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours muſt be impowred to require the belief of or poſitive aſſent unto theſe Fundamendal Articles, as being otherwiſe unable to ſecure the Being, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt the ruine of that Church, of which they are a part. When therefore M. <hi>S.</hi> ſo confidently gives out (without all manner of exceptions) that our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106628:30"/>Church is <hi>Shamefac'd of obliging others to believe her, p.</hi> 194. and that <hi>ſhe profeſſeth her ſelf very heartily content with external obedience, let the interior aſſent go where it will: p.</hi> 199. I cannot but admire, that ſo ingenious a perſon ſhould vent ſuch things, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day confutes, and tell our Church, ſhe expects not that her members ſhould believe that Creed which ſhe eſteems her fundamentals, inſerts into her Catechiſms, requires us to Agnize in Baptiſme, rehearſe in all her Sacred offices, and that with a peculiar circumſtance deſigned to ſignifie our aſſent unto and readineſs to defend it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But do you not <hi>in big words ask when did ſhe challenge any power over our minds &amp; conſciences? p.</hi> 198. And doth not M. <hi>S.</hi> well infer, that therefore you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſhe requires an interior aſſent. <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, theſe things are vaſtly different, require interior aſſent he may, who being authorized to guide me in matters of faith can <hi>evidence</hi> what he thus requires to be the will of God revealed, yea ſuch interior aſſent is due from Children to their Parents, from Servants to their Maſters, much mere from People to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors when evidencing their duty to them, but <hi>challenge power over the mind and conſcience,</hi> he only can who is Lord of the conſcience, &amp; whoſe laws by an immediate virtue bind the conſcience, for what binds only mediately, hath not this obligatory power from any virtue of the Legiſlator over the mind and conſcience, but only from that power which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the conſcience to obey ſuch Legiſlators.</p>
               <p>And if interiour aſſent may be required, I wonder why it ſhould be more irrational, <hi>to go about to lay an obligation on the Cathol. p.</hi> 199. by theſe two Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, then upon the Proteſtant
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106628:30"/>(as my Friend imagines.) That it ſhould be rational to bind the loyal Subject by thoſe Oaths, but irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional to bind thoſe whoſe Treacheries and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies firſt made them neceſſary, if <hi>difference of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> be a juſt exemption, then may the <hi>Quaker, Anabaptiſt,</hi> and other turbulent perſons which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our Church, plead for a ſhare in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption, and King and Parliament muſt be unjuſt and tyrannous in laying ſuch a burthen on them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 4. A particular Church cannot require this aſſent upon pretence of an infallible aſſiſtance,) (for ſeeling all have the like title to it, it would be impoſisible for any of them to have erred) and therefore ſhe muſt do it becauſe the thing determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is ſo evident in the Rule of Faith, that all deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of it muſt be wilful, for ſeeing 'tis already proved that ſhe hath power to require this aſſent, and that this power cannot derive from an infallible aſsiſtance, what remains, but that it bottom upon the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the thing? But then the query is, <hi>Who muſt be judge what is ſo evident in Scripture, as to render the diſſertors guilty of flat wilfulneſs. p.</hi> 195.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Faith being an aſſent, and conſequently the reſult of judgment, each private perſon muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his judgment of diſcretion, much more thoſe who are authorized to require our aſſent to funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, and to preſerve the peace and union of the Church inviolable, and ſure 'twould be a great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment to our Saviour, to intruſt perſons with the preſervation of this <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> and to require them to give heed to it, as they will anſwer it at the great day, and yet afford no means to be aſſured of it. <hi>But if each private perſon muſt have a judgment of diſcretion by which he muſt admit of, or reject the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106628:31"/>laws of his ſuperiors,</hi> (&amp; if it ſhould be otherwiſe men muſt renounce their reaſon, &amp; reject the guidance of their conſcience, and ſo of Gods Vicegerent, &amp; act in the concernments of their eternal ſouls at all adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) <hi>who ſhall paſs judgement on the final and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable judge:</hi> thus <hi>Fiat lux, Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 198.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Conſcience being ſubject unto none but God (who only knows the ſecrets of it) he only can paſs judgement of its actions and pretences, and he aſſuredly will convince the Shiſmatick and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick twas not their Reaſon but their luſts that did betray them to ſuch errors, but the reſults of ſuch a Judgement which interfere with the received do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or cuſtomes of the Church, muſt ſo far be condemned and cenſured by the Superiors of the Church, as they do interrupt the Peace and Unity thereof. The Jews were bound to hearken to the Scribes and Phariſees the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> and High-Prieſt, (and they had power to chaſtiſe their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in lawful matters) and yet I hope with that diſcretion which was requiſite to preferve them from condemning our <hi>Meſſias</hi> for a cheat, or for embracing thoſe Traditions which did evacuate the Law of God, for otherwiſe our Saviour was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much to blame, when he ſo often taught the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and put in ſo many caveats againſt the leaven of the Scribes and Phariſees. Thus Rulers are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for a terror unto evil doers, and an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement unto the Good, and conſequently muſt have ſurficient means to be inſtructed in that Good or evil which they are to reward or puniſh, and power ſo to do, and yet inferiors are forbid to yeild obedience to their unlawful precepts, and in ſuch caſes are to prefer obedience to the Laws of God,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106628:31"/>which muſt ſuppoſe a judgement of diſcretion in them to diſcern what precepts are unlawful, and when they interſere with the unerring rule of Scripture ſo well conſiſtent is the judgement of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion, we allow to private perſons, both with the power of Superiors and Peace and Unity of the Church.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>But I denyed them to be judges of Faith: Now to be clearly revealed, or evident in Scripture, and to be of Faith is all one ſo that they muſt not be judges of what is evident in Scripture, least by neceſſary conſequence, they become judges of Faith too. p.</hi> 195.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Argument ſuppoſeth that to be judge <hi>of Faith,</hi> and to be <hi>judge of what is Faith,</hi> are terms equivalent, which is a great miſtake, to judge what is Faith, and what is evidently revealed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is the buſineſs of each Catechiſt and Preacher who declares the Articles of Faith, of each belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver who aſſents unto them becauſe his judgement tels him they are ſuch, and therefore ſignally the work of them with whom this Faith is viſibly intruſted, but to be judge of Faith, or to be that <hi>perſon or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munity whoſe judgment in ſuch matters muſt be infallibly received without farther ſcrutiny,</hi> is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative as clearly incompetent to any perſon: or community as it is vehemently pretended to, 'twas <hi>Sir</hi> upon this ſlender Cobweb your doughty infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence did hang.</p>
               <p>Ob. 2. <hi>You refuſe to admit them as Guides of their Faith, which ſignifies they may have power to require our aſſents in matters in which they have no power to guide us, i. e. they may have power to require us to go wrong for any thing we or they know. p.</hi> 195.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let me again inform you that to guid <hi>others in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106628:32"/>their faith,</hi> or <hi>to it,</hi> and <hi>to be guide of Faith,</hi> are things extreamly differring: whoever doth inſtruct his Brother in any matter of Faith, or reclaim him from his Error, becomes a <hi>charitative Guide</hi> unto Faith; whoever by the Church is authorized ſo to do, becomes an <hi>Authoritative Guide</hi> unto Faith: but to be guide of Faith (eſpecially in that ſence in which this phraſe is taken in our preſent Controverſie) is <hi>to be ſuch a one whoſe judgement muſt determine for us what is Faith, what not;</hi> and thus our Reaſon onely is our Guide in matters dubious.</p>
               <p>Ob: 3. <hi>But what can be replyed to a Socinian, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when his aſſent to the Trinity is required, That he humbly ſubmitted to Scrip. that he uſed al means he could, but diſcovered it not ſo evident there as you conceive it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> The very ſame you would return unto your Brother <hi>Carpocratian,</hi> pretending as humble a ſubmiſſion to your Rule of Faith, and yet conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thence for Hereſie; or to the Proteſtant, aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tradition where it may be had, to be as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick as the written Word; and yet proteſting, That after all means uſed, he could never finde therein one footſtep of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith; or laſtly, to the <hi>Arrian</hi> of old, or new <hi>Photinian,</hi> who both laid claim to the Tradition of the three firſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies: In a word, the onely anſwer you can make to ſuch Enquiries, muſt be this, <hi>That your appeal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Tradition is both true and juſt, ſo was not that of the</hi> Photmian <hi>or</hi> Carpocratian <hi>Heretick:</hi> And ſurely then the like return of Proteſtants to the <hi>Socinian, Quaker, Independant,</hi> when pretending the ſame reaſon for their ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which we do from that of <hi>Rome,</hi> if founded upon real Truth, muſt vindicate our Church from all your clamors.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:106628:32"/>
               <p>Object: <hi>But upon the ſame right and title that we ſeparated from</hi> Rome, <hi>did Independants, Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. depart from us; <hi>for ſince they do it upon their own diſcretion, and ſo upon our Principle, to deny it to be done by them ſo juſtly,</hi> or <hi>ſo truly, is to do wickedly, and talk fondly, Fiat Lux</hi> Ep: 2. p. 198, 199. or which is <hi>trantamount,</hi> to do and talk after the manner of <hi>fiat lux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> As if not onely the <hi>Carpocration,</hi> but the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> ſhould be thought to act as juſtly and as truly as the beſt of Catholicks, becauſe as ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement Alſertors of the Traditions of their Fathers, and all the Actions and Sentiments of Mankinde ſhould carry equal Truth and Juſtice in them, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally the products of what they looked on as reaſon and diſcretion: Thus <hi>Saul</hi> the Perſecutor muſt act as juſtly, as <hi>Paul</hi> the Doctor of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, becauſe according to his Conſcience; and the Catholick, when Preaching to convert, and practiſing to deſtroy his Prince, muſt do both with equal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, provided that his good intentions to propagate the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, be alike in both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop:</hi> 5. In matters which belong not to the Foundations of our Faith, to be content with ſuch ſubmiſſion as is conſiſtent with a liberty of opinion, and binds us onely to reſerve our Judgements to our ſelves, in what they differ from the profeſſed Doctrine of the Church we live in, ſeems moſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the ends of Peace and Unity; to the ends of Peace, becauſe it leſſeneth the Objects, and ſo withdraws the fewel of Contention; of Unity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it much enlargeth the conditions of it, and rendreth them ſuch, as may more eaſily be ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:106628:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coroll:</hi> Hence 'tis apparently moſt ſafe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, to be content with this ſubmiſſion, as being moſt conducive to the Peace and Union that is unto the Soveraign ends of Chriſtian Government; and is it not unreaſonable that Men ſhould be excluded by the Church from her Communion, for what is very well conſiſtent with our communion with the God of Heaven, our union to the Churches Head; yea, for what is neither neceſſary to the Churches being, peace or unity, nor can be prejudicial to them, whileſt reſerved to our ſelves? Beſides, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Church communion, muſt bottom upon what is clear and evident, for elſe the Union of the Church, and our duty to preſerve it, muſt both reſt on what's uncertain and obſcure (a thing repugnant both to the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of the Churches Head) now that in matters remote from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we have moſtly no ſuch evidence, is but too viſible in the Diſputes and Conteſts which are on both ſides managed by many Learned and impartial Men. To conclude, Let any Man conſider the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Gifts, Affections, Prejudices, and infinite other Circumſtances, that are incident to humane Nature: and then tell me, whether it be not irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional to hope, That all the Members of a Church, in matters of this nature, ſhould conſpire, and knit into one Faith and Judgement? and muſt it not be more unreaſonable, to make this Union the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of communion with the Church? If therefore in theſe matters our Church contents her ſelf with this ſubmiſſion, and doth not binde us to declare our inward aſſent, ſhe acts both prudently and ſafely, and as becometh an indulgent Mother.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:106628:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop:</hi> 6. The Church hath power to ſilence ſuch Diſputes as tend immediately to break her peace and unity: This is ſo proper a reſult of civil Union, as that without it, all Government muſt ſhatter into Sects and Factions, and therefore moſt of all may be expected in that Platform which our Savior laid, and muſt be granted by all thoſe, who dare not think our Lord defective in his Deſigns and Contrivances for his Churches Peace and Unity: In a word, Each Church is bound to look to her own Peace, and therefore is impowred to prevent what violates it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop:</hi> 7. All Men are bound, whatever their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Sentiments may be, to ſubmit externally to the ſentence of the Church, in matters which entrench not on the Fundamentals of their Faith, becauſe the teaching of ſuch Doctrines muſt be of leſſer moment then the preſervation of the Churches peace; for ſhould ſuch Doctrines wholly periſh from the Church, her Peace, Unity and Being, might be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently preſerved notwithſtanding, whereas this cannot reaſonably be hoped for under an eager vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent abetment of them in deſpite of all Authority; and certainly, if Church-Governors ſtand bound unto the preſervation of the Churches Peace and Unity, they muſt be bound in many inſtances to ſtill our mutual Conteſts, and require the ſubmiſſion now intended, and then the governed muſt be obliged to perform it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop:</hi> 8. No Church can juſtly require aſſent unto her Propoſals, or account of her infallibility; for were this Priviledge vouchſafed to the Church, is it not wonderful that a Doctrine ſo neceſſary to the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſalvation ſhould either be conceaſed from the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106628:34"/>four Evangelifts, or by them (if not concealed yet) ſo obſcurely delivered to the Church? Can we ſuppoſe theſe wiſe and holy Men (and eſpecially that good ſpirit which aſſiſted them) either ſo envious as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to deprive the Church of ſuch an happineſs, for whoſe proſperity they ſuffered ſo much, and which they almoſt Chriſtned with their Blood; or ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of the Work they took in hand, <hi>viz.</hi> the writing of the Goſpel of Chriſt, as to neglect the clear reherſal of that Doctrine, without which (if the Papiſt may be credited) all others are not cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable? 'tis evident, they ſpeak perſpicuouſly of many things of ſmall importance in compariſon of this, and is it poſsible they ſhould conſpire to the deepeſt ſilence or obſcurity in this moſt neceſſary thing, this fundamental of all that is ſo? Is it ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable that S. <hi>Luke,</hi> intending purpoſely to ſatisfie <hi>Theophilus</hi> in theſe things wherein he had been Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed, and which moſt ſurely were believed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, ſhould neglect this great Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of them all, without which, Faith muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſuffer Shipwrack, and all his labor be in vain? That the beloved Apoſtle having writ ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſigns, that we might believe <hi>that Jeſus is the Son of God,</hi> ſhould neglect that, without which, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that he ſaid could be available to produce Faith in us, or ſecure us from miſtaking in it? It is poſſible that our Saviour, who foreſaw whatever might diſturb his Church, yea, had experience of Mens unwillingneſs to ſubmit to others, and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to advance themſelves in his own Diſciples, ſhould yet deliver this Doctrine (if at all delivered) ſo obſcurely, that now it is become the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, whether he intended any thing of this
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106628:34"/>nature? and the teſtimonies of Scripture ſo ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly baffled, that Papiſts dare not go about to vindicate them from our Exceptions? That he ſhould conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute that to be the onely means of deciding Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, which he foreſaw would be ſo determinable without the certain knowledge of ſome hundreds of Particulars, in which whole thouſands of Men, excellent for Parts and Piety, do claſh perpetually? That under the Old Teſtament, the Judge of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters between blood and blood, plea and plea, and ſuch Political Tranſactions, ſhould be ſo punctually ſet down: And in the New Teſtament, this Judge of Faith, and the eternal Concernments of our Souls, ſhould be paſſed over in ſilence, or delivered in ſuch terms as are equally adapted to all pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to be the Church, and altogether unſerviceable when 'tis doubtful? Is it not ſtrange, that ſo great a part of the New Teſtament ſhould be employed about Antichriſt, and all the methods he ſhould uſe to draw Men from the Faith, and yet juſt nothing be delivered of that Guide to which all faithful Chriſtians were to have recourſe againſt him? That the Spirit ſhould ſpeak expreſly, of ſome <hi>great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the Faith in theſe latter times,</hi> and not admoniſh us of the ſure and onely means to ſecure our falling: That St. <hi>Paul,</hi> amongſt all his vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Exhortations unto Unity, all his endeavors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Schiſm in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and elſewhere, ſhould not once deliver this unto them as a means infallibly to preſerve them from it, but ſpend his time in other matters, which, without this, are not at all available to our ſouls welfare? That having aſſembled the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and told them, That after his departure, grievous Wolves ſhould
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106628:35"/>enter in among them, he ſhould not once direct hem to the onely means for preſervation? That the Apoſtles in the compiling of the Creed, ſhould give no intimation of that, without which, nothing can hang firm? That <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian, Cyprians,</hi> and others, purpoſely delivering the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of their Faith, ſhould be deficient in the like kinde? That never any of the Primitive Fathers in their Comments on this Symbol, ſhould inform us of <hi>this one thing neceſſary?</hi> That they ſhould talk ſo much of the Catholick Church, and not one title of its infallibility? That in their deſcants on theſe Paſſages, which are ſo often pleaded by the <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> they ſhould never intimate unto us that in the Judgement of the Catholick Church, or at leaſt their own, they taught infallibility? That the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, albeit they had ſo great occaſion from the multiplying of Hereſies, to have inſiſted upon this ſo Fundamental Doctrine (that each Mans Soul muſt bottom on it, or be built upon the Sand) ſhould not onely wave the ſtating, clearing, confirming, or the trying of it, but compoſe a Creed, and never mention it? That the <hi>Catechumeni</hi> ſhould never be taught this foundation of their Faith? That it ſhould never be required at Baptiſm? That none of the Treatiſes <hi>ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lechumenos, Inſtitutiones Myſtagogice, Enchiridia Doctrina Chriſtianae?</hi> None of the Treatiſes of the Church her ſelf, ſhould once make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this great and principal Funamental, is, as if a Man ſhould write of the chief Cities in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and leave out <hi>York</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> or of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Hierarchy in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and leave out Pope and Cardinal? laſtly, That whereas ſince the Uſurpation of this Prerogative by the Church
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106628:35"/>of <hi>Rome</hi> there have been hundreds of Diſputes touching the ſubject of its infallibility, whether Chriſt were here or there, without determining of which to affirme in groſs the Churches infallibility is to leave us perfectly in a maze, &amp; ſay juſt nothing, that not any of thoſe diſputes ſhould ever be ſtarted, nor any thing reſolved upon? Theſe are things morally impoſſible and conſequently this pretended infallibility muſt be ſo: this being ſo 'tis ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to refute the pretence of a General Council to it, for beſides what already hath been ſaid, can it be that whats ſo neceſſary to the welfare to the Church ſhould by an all-wiſe God be left at infinite uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties? A general Council is infallible ſay they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that it be legitimately called, &amp; that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it be legitimate, that they be legally elected, and in due number from every part and portion of the Church; that being thus convened they vote freely and without conſtraint, and packing: after due Means of Study, Prayer and faſting uſed; provided laſtly that the decree conciliarly, have theſe decrees confirmed by the <hi>Pope,</hi> and accepted by the Church, diffuſed, if one of theſe conditions be wanting to the greateſt Councils they take liberty to reject them, &amp; yet who knows not what animoſities, and feuds there are in the now preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (and much more in the Church of God) touching the greater part of Councils ſtyled Oeconomical? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all theſe conditions have been punctually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by them in the whole, and each particular Decree? how more then probable it is that like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties ſhould ariſe touching the definitions of future Councils? &amp; how impoſſible it is for any, (but eſpecially for perſons illiterate &amp; far removed from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106628:36"/>the place of their Convention) to attain to any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable ſatisfaction in all theſe particulars? This ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is by the wiſer ſort of Papiſts handſomely paſſed over as knowing it to be unanſwerable; but <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> hath ignorance enough to warrant his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts upon it, which are theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That we may as well except againſt the obliging power of the decrees and Acts of King and Parliament, and ſay, is that power in the King alone, or in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, what if they run counter, what if they ſhould not be rightly Choſen. p.</hi> 190.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But dares he ſay that one of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are undetermined by our Law? Dares he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch that the obliging power of our Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments depends on ſuch a multitude of things, of which no tolerable aſſurance can be had? If ſo, he evidently ſtands guilty not only of Rebellion, but juſtifies the late Phanatick, aſſuring him that he may ſafely queſtion and oppoſe the power both of King and Parliament, as depending on ſome hundreds of uncertainties, as hotly conteſted, and as unreſolved by the Lawyers of the Land, as the forementioned Decrees of Councils are in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> If not how groſs moſt his impertinence and folly be, in bringing ſuch compariſons which both his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and his reaſon tell him are vaſtly different from what his adverſary produceth? And yet ſecondly, who knows not that a leſs degree of certainty may ſuffice in civil, then in ſacred matters.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, he takes Sanctuary in <hi>Titulus colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus, and moral evidence,</hi> and tels us, <hi>that if this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice not we can be ſure of no Authority either Spiritual or Civil in this world. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> And is this that <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> who writ a pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106628:36"/>of infallibility? Made it ſo neceſſary for the Churches welfare, that without it <hi>nothing can hang firm nor Chriſt be juſt, p.</hi> 5, 6. had he not provided ſuch aſſurance for our faith to build upon, is he now content to ſit down with <hi>Titulus Coloratus,</hi> &amp; moral evidence? And to confeſs that Catholick Faith, and the Authority of the Church depends upon ſo many and ſuch various conditions for which they do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend but moral evidence? Is not this moral evidence the very thing at which the Romaniſt doth ſo much quarrel in the reſolution of our Faith? And muſt it now become the refuge of thoſe very men who do ſo vehemently cry out againſt it in the Proteſtant; See here the triumph and the Victory of Truth, which forceth her profeſſed adverſaries to agnize and own her though to the ruine of their cauſe and credit, and yet manifeſt it is that few of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars objected will admit of moral evidence, or any tollerable degree of probability.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corol.</hi> 1. Hence ſee the excellency of our Churches method for peace and unity beyond what <hi>Rome</hi> can boaſt of, ſeeing then only ſhe require our aſſent, when the revelation is ſo clear and palpable that he who runs may read it, and when the thing is ſuch, as hath the teſtimony and approbation of the whole Chriſtian World, handed down from the Apoſtles, to this preſent age, and acknowledged to be ſuch by Catholicks themſelves. And in other things reſts contented with that ſubmiſſion which is conſiſtent with mens liberty of conſcience, and each mans du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to afford her, whereas <hi>Rome</hi> doth not only bind the <hi>conſcience</hi> to whats unneceſſary, unheard of in the Churches Creeds till now of late, and ſo obſcure as to be matter of conteſt through the Chriſtian world,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106628:37"/>but doth all this upon pretence of that infallibility woh were it only queſtionable, muſt ſubject us to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of embracing the moſt deſtructive errors for divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt truths, without all hopes of a redreſs, diſpoſe us unto Atheiſme, and irreligion, by making all our Faith and piety depend on what is diſputable, and lay us open to continnal fears and jealouſies, doubts and uncertainties, Schiſms and diſſentions, about the rule and foundation of our Faith, but being evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe, muſt be moſt certainly productive of theſe fatal conſequences, and yet we muſt be told with ſo much confidence: <hi>p.</hi> 200. <hi>That plaineſt common ſence will teach us and every man who conſiders it, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we ſettle ſome indiſputable method of arriving at Chriſts ſence, or faith, that is, ſome ſelf-evident (and ſo all obliging) Rule of Faith, the Proteſtant Church can never hope for power to reduce their diſſenters, nor to hold together or govern efficaciouſly their own ſubjects, that is, they can never hope for unity within themſelves or union with them that have it.</hi> Which in effect, is thus much, <hi>That both his ſacred Majeſtie, and all his Peers and Prelates, Laity, and Clergy, are profeſt oppoſers of what plaineſt common ſence, and each mans Reaſon muſt ſuggeſt unto him as the ſole expedient of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches welfare;</hi> for which great charity, and worthy thoughts of our whole Nation, 'tis pitty but it ſhould be ordered by the King and Parliament, that <hi>due thanks be given to</hi> Mr. <hi>S.</hi> eſpecially ſeeing he hath been at the vaſt expence of an <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> to confirm the charge, hower <hi>contenti ſumus hoc Catone,</hi> nor have we need to add <hi>homine imprudenti at que imperito ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bil quicquam injuſtius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. This ſhews what ſpirit of Divination had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed my <hi>friend</hi> when thus he talks, <hi>Hence we may ſee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106628:37"/>confeſſedly in the Proteſtant principles the Reaſon of their preſent and paſt diſtractions, and divine of the future, for mens fancies being naturally various, &amp; no power in her to keep them in union, they muſt needs ramble into multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Diſſenting Sects, which to ſtrive to unite in one, were to force both nature and conſcience too. Nature in ſtriving to unite their underſtandings in Faith, without offering them evidence of Authority, conſcience in bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to act as Proteſtants do, whereas they are ready to ſtake their Salvation upon it, that their beſt reaſons working upon the very Rule of Faith, Proteſtants recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, obliges them to the contrary.</hi> For firſt in funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, in which onely we think it neceſſary to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the underſtandings of our people, we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly all the evidence that Scripture and Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (the Role of Proteſtants and Papiſts) can afford. And ſecondly, in other matters we have power to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſuch diſputes, and prevent the ſpreading of ſuch opinions as may cauſe diviſions, and inflict the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cenſures upon thoſe that do ſo, and conſequently have ſufficient proviſions for that peace and unity, which is neceſſary to the Churches welfare. And thirdly, either we do not bind the conſcience, and therefore cannot force it, or elſe we do it upon that pregnant evidence now mentioned, and therefore cannot be ſaid <hi>to oblige the will againſt the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> And laſtly, we are as ready to proteſt <hi>that our beſt reaſon working upon the very rule of Faith, which Romaniſts recommend unto us, obligeth us to renounce their faith, and that to force us to act with them, would be to force our conſciences unto ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For a cloſe to cry quit with you, this ſhews the reaſon of that General Atheiſm, Scepticiſm and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion which is ſpread over the face of the whole
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106628:38"/>Roman Church, which prevails ſo much in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and makes <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian, little differ from her ſelf whilſt Heathen, for having built her Faith upon that infallibility which ſtands liable to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of doubts, and is confuted by variety of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Experiences, what remains but that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion periſh in its ruines. Once more this ſhews the reaſon of the ſudden growth of Atheiſm in this our Nation, for Catholicks having by experience found that all their endeavours muſt be fruitleſs whileſt we have Scripture for our Rule, that whilſt Chriſtianity ſtands upon its old foundations, their politick profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it cannot find <hi>ſure footing</hi> in our Nation, have at laſt made it their profeſſed buſineſs to draw the night upon her, to wipe out Scripture at one daſh, and pronounce all thoſe arguments which the firſt Champions of Chriſtianity made uſe of, unſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and null, that being thus benighted even by a <hi>fiat lux,</hi> we might take up with an implicite faith, and being firſt made Atheiſts, be in a nearer diſpoſition to act the Papiſt: And laſtly, that finding no <hi>ſure foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the Scriptures, we might run unto Tradition for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:106628:38"/>
               <head>An Appendix containing an Anſwer to thoſe few paſſages in <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> which beare ſome ſhew of Reaſon, and might poſſibly deceive the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Reader.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THerefore 'tis aſſerted, <hi>That the power of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing to the Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome mentioned in the Council of Sardica was ad Julium Romanum, not ad Papam Romanum, and ſo a perſonvl priviledge, which might ceaſe on the death of Julius, p.</hi> 59. that is, quoth <hi>Fiat Lux, not to the pope who then was Julius, but to Julius who then was Pope p.</hi> 55. Whereas he ſhould have ſaid not to him <hi>as Pope,</hi> but as <hi>Julius, i.e.</hi> as one depoſed and reviled by the Faſtern Biſhops againſt whom this Council did oppoſe themſelves, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to advance him, as much as they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to depreſs, and vilifie him, but alas <hi>materia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter</hi> and <hi>formaliter</hi> are terms which the poor man is wholly unacquainted with, and this anſwer was grounded upon Hiſtory which neither his <hi>Don Quixot</hi> nor <hi>Hudibras</hi> would afford him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'twas above his ſhallow capacity.</p>
               <p>Twas ſecondly aſſerted that the Doctrine ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as a Doctrine of Divels was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that of thoſe in general that forbid mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, not condemn it upon ſuch and ſuch particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</hi> And therefore though the <hi>Encratite</hi> &amp; <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt</hi> were deeper yet they alſo did participate in the guilt. <hi>p.</hi> 210. <hi>To convince this anſwer of folly &amp; falſehood</hi> it is thus rejoyned, <hi>That if ſo 'twould follow that the Church of England muſt be guilty of the Doctrine of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106628:39"/>Divels by prohibiting marriage in the times of Lent and Advent, p.</hi> 182. <hi>A.</hi> as if it were all one to forbid the thing, and to reſtrain the doing of it at times unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> had been as great a criminal for adviſing abſtinence from due Benevolence at times of extraordinary prayer and faſting as they who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies thought it neceſſary to do ſo, and laſtly to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid fleſh in general, and to forbid it upon daies of faſting and humiliation, were things equivalent; tis I confeſs the ſame to forbid it at times unfit, and unto perſons to whom it is ſo, but never will it be evinced that that <hi>marriage which is honourable in all,</hi> be undecent in the Clergy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>But do you not acknowledge their fundamentals to be ſo perſpicuous as what is written with a Sun beam, and therefore ſuch as none but fools can poſſibly miſtake in, and is it not then juſtly wondred by</hi> Fiat Lux, <hi>that any Proteſtant writers ſhould affirm that general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils who have Authority from Chriſt of deciding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, greater aſſiſtance in, and means of finding out the truth then others ſhould lye under a poſſibility of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in what is ſo perſpicuous and cleare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This objection doth as much concern the Catholick as us, who albeit he pretends <hi>infallible,</hi> and ſo the greateſt <hi>evidence,</hi> for matters of his Faith, yet cannot, but acknowledge that they are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted not only by the <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> but a confiderable part of the <hi>Western</hi> Church: Doth not my Friend, and all his brother Catholicks aſſert, <hi>That the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Church, is ſuch a motive to beliefe, that only irrational, vicious and willfully blind perſons can recede from it by disbelief, S.F.p.</hi> 197. &amp; yet have not its definitions been ſolemnly condemned by <hi>Arriau</hi> Councils as great as any they ſtile general? And by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106628:39"/>the Provincial Councils of the Reformed Churches, are not theſe condemnations, ſubſcribed, propugned and adjuſted by far greater multitudes of learned men then ever did convene in General Councils? and what is incident to them diffuſed, why may it not be incident to a far leſs number when convened? Nay ſecondly was not the law of Nature, were not the Notions of a Deity ſo manifeſt and obvious as to render the offender <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or condemned of his own conſcience? And yet were not the greater part of men ſuch fools for many hundreds of years together, to act in contradiction to them? Was not the Doctrine of our Saviour confirmed by ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, ſuch Prophecies and other ſignal evidenes as rendred it unqueſtionably true, and the rejectors of it inexcuſable: and did not yet the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> and Jew, reject it and Blaſpheme it though convinced of its truth: nay is not the generality of the learned world (much more the giddy and unruly muititude) ſo inconſiderate as to run headlong to that ruine which dayly lays before their eyes, and no wonder that it ſhould be ſo ſince the Church ſtory ſhews too plainly that intereſt, pride, and faction, prejudice, falſe principles, and a miſtaken Rule of Faith, have but too often acted in the Rulers of the Church: yea even Reaſon and Experience informs us that ſuch perſons have moſt ſubtilty to elude the plaineſt arguments, and moſt concluding Reaſons, to find out contrary pretences to oppoſe againſt them, and many other artifices to bind their Faith unto their intereſts.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
